<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2016-12-05T00:03:59+08:00</updated><id>http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/</id><title type="html">lieu’s site</title><subtitle>my personal site</subtitle><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><entry><title type="html">ORD lo</title><link href="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/12/03/ORD-lo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ORD lo" /><published>2016-12-03T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-12-03T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/12/03/ORD-lo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/12/03/ORD-lo.html">&lt;p&gt;these two chrysalid years are finally over
this is a period of unprecedented freedom and it’s imperative i don’t waste my time&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I’ve to do for the month of December:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Catch up to the original plan of 52 books (give myself discount la, 50 will do.)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Currently: 43 books).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;7 books in 4 weeks&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finish CS50!!! This is a MUST:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Problem Set 6&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Problem Set 7&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Problem Set 8&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Final project&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cut to 67kg bodyweight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="monthly review" /><category term="progress report" /><summary type="html">these two chrysalid years are finally over
this is a period of unprecedented freedom and it’s imperative i don’t waste my time</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">October in review; plans for November</title><link href="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/10/28/october-in-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="October in review; plans for November" /><published>2016-10-28T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-10-28T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/10/28/october-in-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/10/28/october-in-review.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/oct_16_calendar.png&quot; alt=&quot;october calendar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;October was the month of MOOCs. I read a grand total of zero books but I started
on CS50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;October was also the month of lapses: I started playing computer games again, spending ~10 hours on Dota 2, ~5 hours on Borderlands 2, and ~10 hours on CrusaderQuest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s &lt;strong&gt;three whole days of work&lt;/strong&gt; assuming 8-hour days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something I’m particularly ashamed of is the fact that I squandered the last week (24–28) after keeping up an admirable momentum for the first two–three weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I estimate that I’ve wasted around 8 days in total of a 28-day month and this is
of course unacceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to start planning my time better. In particular, after I ORD I will have
the freedom to structure my time to a far greater extent. No hour should be
wasted—this is the minimum modicum of discipline that I should expect from
myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other news, I realised that I’ve hit the 85kg 5x5 stated in my “current
projects” page. I also managed to bench 105kg ORM—I will update the current projects page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;projects-for-november&quot;&gt;Projects for November&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are my current projects for the month of November:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Smart home project
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The issue I’m currently facing now is a problem with serial output coming
 from Arduino. Instead of receiving data every line, sometimes I receive the
 data as follows: “line1 \n line2” as one data object.
 Mark suggested I write a buffer to print out the data line by line but…I’m
 not sure how to do it and have been putting it off.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Co{de}llective website
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This has to be up by 12th November: non-negotiable.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I’ve to get the site up and write some articles… shag af&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I realise that I’m less and less interested in webdev, at least building
 static websites… I learn nothing from it and it’s just really dull.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CS50: finish it up
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I started CS50 1st October and managed to do 5 problem sets in one month. I
 hope to be able to finish up CS50x by November and then start MIT’s
 Analytics Edge in December.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scholarships: look for and apply for them
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I have blocked off the months of Dec and Jan for travel. (December with
family; January with class) Hence, there won’t     be time for me to do
anything serious then.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;My scholarship deadlines are March—that means I have only one month + to
prepare and submit my scholarships.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;That’s why it’s important to start looking now (after November 12).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;currently-worrying-about&quot;&gt;Currently worrying about&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ORD
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I realise that I’m not looking forward to ORD as much as I should. I really
 wanted to ORD but now that it’s right around the horizon the sense of
 freedom has been relpaced with some sort of dread and I’m not (as) keen to
 ORD. The dread is the recognition that I will have an enormous block of free
 time and I will have the responsiblity of using it properly.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;There are also things that I previously took for granted in the army but
 can’t anymore: for example, I’ve to find a new gym and pay for it (TGN is 8
 dollars an entry; membership at 75 dollars a month)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scholarship
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Critical if I’m to go to Oxford—enough said&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Major choice
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Change major or no? Tech is becoming more and more relevant and I’m not sure
 about the relevance of a PPE degree.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="monthly review" /><category term="progress report" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An eventful Saturday</title><link href="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/10/08/an-eventful-saturday.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An eventful Saturday" /><published>2016-10-08T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-10-08T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/10/08/an-eventful-saturday</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/10/08/an-eventful-saturday.html">&lt;p&gt;I woke up at 8:30 a.m. today and did a bit of Problem Set 4 in CS50.  Then I
went to teach the C4C P5 class (Dylan, Gao Hong, Audrey and Gillian).  Last
week, I taught them lessons 1 and 2 (the input and print command) and this week
I taught Python Turtle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have reproduced my message to the C4C P5 group here, as it nicely sums up how
the lesson went:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/audrey_gillian_yi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image posted by zhengyang&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;just to add a bit of context to Zheng Yang’s post, and a post-mortem of today’s
lesson:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have been teaching them Python for two weeks now according to my curriculum.
Last week they learned four main things: 
  - the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;print()&lt;/code&gt; function, 
  - the concept of variables, 
  - taking user input with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;input()&lt;/code&gt; and
  - type conversion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We spent the first ~45 minutes of the day on recapping those four things.
Then we moved on to the next lesson, which is drawing with Python’s turtle
module.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The kids were all able to grasp the concept of the turtle very quickly— this
bolsters my confidence in Turtle as a teaching tool.  And the photo by Zheng
Yang is the Chinese character 易 done by Audrey and Gillian. I think it is
very nice.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Overall, all the lesson objectives were met and I was pleased with the
progress of the lesson. Audrey, Gillian and Dylan were focused and
well-behaved, Gao Hong not so much (but still relatively tractable). I would
like especially to commend Dylan, who went to the library to borrow a book
about Python programming on his own accord! Very pleased with his interest and
I feel that given his young age, he will be an accomplished coder very soon as
long as we continue to stoke his interest and challenge him. Maybe it’s not
too early to think about &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt; DSA…. 😂&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;One last thing —thanks to Zhen Yang and Poe for coming today. 
I hope to see all you guys again next week!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I met Mrs Hauw after the lesson. She had approached me earlier this week to
offer me an internship at Iglobe once I finish NS. She said on Telegram that the
internship would take about 6-8 months and I expressed this concern to her.
Whereupon she said “Since when I said 6-8 months? I told you Yau Xuan interned
for 6 months, you only need to do 4 months”…which was weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had some other concerns but she waved them aside… I told her that I had to
apply for scholarships whereupon she said “Aiya your scholarship need to apply
full time meh?” or something along those lines. She mentioned that she had
already received applications from undergraduates. I asked her how I would
represent skills that are non-credentialed (i.e. basically all programming
skills) and she said that it will show in the interview. I then asked “Then do I
have to do the interview?” and she smiled and said “I already interviewed you
already what.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She gave me some more tips about writing the CV and told me that “there’s no
such thing as modesty” when I said that I was reluctant to put non-credentialed
skills on my CV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I have read her correctly (and I could be wrong…) she is basically saying
that the CV is a mere formality and she already wants me for the job. 
But either way I
have to write a CV and make it a good one since this CV isn’t just for this
internship application, it’s for all subsequent applications so best to bite the
bullet and do it now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like I have a strong focus right now–tech, and teaching tech. I am
fortunate to have free rein over what I can teach the kids. That gives
me an advantage over others who may not be as focused in their CIP. But more on
strategic CV writing in a later post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After C4C and the meeting with Mrs Hauw I went to the gym with Chew (Delta Gym)
and both Chew and I failed all our lifts. It wasn’t even a good fail it was a
totally embarassing fail… like 2 reps and can’t push any more kind of fail.
Meh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-joosy-part&quot;&gt;The joosy part&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is when the really joosy part comes in. So after gym we called up Nauxiy
and asked him to join us for dinner. We agreed to meet at Star Vista.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Buona MRT, while we were taking the escalator down, Chew pointed out to me 
an old Indian man who looked like he was stuck on the escalator. From what we
could see, because he kept moving backward, it looked like his leg was stuck in
the escalator! I quickly ran down only to see the guy walking backwards,
barefoot, like it was the most normal thing in the world. He was facing the
“right” way (that is, the normal way) but walking backwards. I must confess that
I was completely taken aback as I had &lt;strong&gt;no fucking idea&lt;/strong&gt; what he was doing and
I just stood there not knowing what to do…
until some guy came behind me and pulled the man off the escalator. One
uncle asked him “Are you drunk?” and he mumbled, grinning, yes I am very drunk.
Thank you very much. 
The
uncle asked him to take the stairs and I watched him climb up the stairs
barefoot (his slippers were upstairs with another Indian man, his friend
probably).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until now I still don’t know what he was trying to do…lol&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had actually thought of pulling the Indian man off the escalator but I was
afraid that he would stumble and fall and really get something caught in the
escalator. I think this shows that my decision-making capability needs work
though I had no idea that he was drunk as I haven’t met many inebriated people
before. Maybe if I had known I would have acted faster. As it was I just stood
there like a fucking idiot lol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-even-joosier-part&quot;&gt;The even joosier part&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the even joosier part. We went to EighteenChefs (the Western food
place run by an ex-convict that specially hires ex-convicts to give them a
second chance). The food there was quite affordable. There was this NSF promotion
where baked cheese rice is only like 7.50 and it tasted pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was this large group of students (I think eight or ten people) who were
seated opposite us. I had my eye on a thick one (hehehe).
We were discussing whether they were poly or uni students but anyway they
finished and left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The waiter, this short guy with big round glasses and a full sleeve on his left 
arm, went
to separate the tables and clean up. I saw him take a phone from the chair and
grin as he walked away. I made a throwaway remark “lol the waiter just took
someone’s phone”. I didn’t think anything of it as I assumed that he was just
taking it for safekeeping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After like ten or fifteen minutes Thick and Thin came in looking very anxious.
They asked the waiter whether he had seen Thick’s phone and the waiter put on a
very concerned face and said no, whereupon he started putting up a big show
looking for the phone under the table and asking them to call the phone. His
&lt;em&gt;wayang&lt;/em&gt; was so good they should have given him golden horse! In fact it was so
good that I was gaslighted. Although I had definitely seen him take the phone I
became not so sure. But nonetheless I walked up to them after the waiter had
left to presumably look for the phone and asked them “You guys are looking for
your phone right?” and told them “I’m pretty sure I saw one of the staff take
your phone” whereupon they asked me, quite naturally, who was the staff member.
Again although I was quite sure it was that guy, I was i) gaslighted and ii) did
not want to accuse someone wrongly so I said that I wasn’t sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then because I was so gaslighted I actually went back to my table and asked the
gang whether I had actually seen the phone being taken? And &lt;em&gt;thank god&lt;/em&gt; I had
made that throwaway remark earlier because they confirmed that I had did indeed
said that and something as specific as “the waiter took a phone” is quite
reliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After five to ten minutes of what must be unadulterated panic felt by the girls,
they managed to get a hold of the manager who told them that he would go and
check the CCTV. After he went in he came out, returned the phone, and told them 
that the phone was
found &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; but to give them their phone number as he wanted to conduct an
“investigation”. I wasn’t smart enough to read the subtext but someone told me
that the manager said “outside” to safeguard the reputation of the restaurant
and in actual fact (of course) it was found in the grubby pockets of that fuckin
thief. Thus vindicated by this fact, I felt secure enough to tell Thick and Thin
that I was pretty sure that it was that waiter who took the phone. (And
apparently Nauxiy said that the waiter gave our table a really dirty look). The
girls thanked me and left. Nauxiy finished his waffle and we left.
江山易改，本性难移!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-could-i-have-done-better&quot;&gt;What could I have done better?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m in two minds about this incident. On the one hand, I think that I handled it
&lt;em&gt;okay&lt;/em&gt; compared to the drunken Indian man incident. But maybe I could have
handled it better? I played it too conservative and Bayesian and kept saying
that I wasn’t sure who the waiter was. But maybe I should have just walked up to
the waiter and told him something alpha like “brother, I saw you take the phone,
give it to us there’s no need to call police”. (And also I could have walked with 
them more all the way to help them solve the incident instead of returning to my table). 
After all, it was a public place,
I was bigger than him and wearing a singlet. But of course these are things that
are really &lt;em&gt;l’esprit de l’escalier&lt;/em&gt;… you fantasise about how you would have
done it in the &lt;strong&gt;cool&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;ALPHA&lt;/strong&gt; way but in the real world when it happens
you’re bo ji and do it the humji way, very 婉转!! And this 婉转 way definitely caused the girls some unnecessary anguish. So I have to train myself to be a more alpha
man and don’t be afraid of confrontation like a pussy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that is the takeaway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other thing (and this one I think it’s a real pity) is that I didn’t get
Thick’s number 😂😂. We were joking about it on the train like “since the
manager asked for her number you should’ve asked for her number too” but more 
and more I’m thinking that &lt;em&gt;maybe&lt;/em&gt; I should have done that… hahaha. After all
you did a good deed so that’s social proof that you’re a Good Person so why not
capitalise on the fact that you did her a huge favour and she has a good
impression of you to get to know her better right??? Of course (as nauxiy
rightly pointed out) that diminishes the goodness of the Good Deed but fuck it,
I don’t live to do good deeds but we literally live to get our dicks wet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also like neither of them thought Thick was chio so &lt;strong&gt;again&lt;/strong&gt; i was
mocked for my low standards and unorthodox taste. But there was a very cute girl
wearing a white dress and a choker (apparently that’s very hot to the two of
them) and we all agreed that she was chio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, that was my eventful Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><summary type="html">I woke up at 8:30 a.m. today and did a bit of Problem Set 4 in CS50.  Then I
went to teach the C4C P5 class (Dylan, Gao Hong, Audrey and Gillian).  Last
week, I taught them lessons 1 and 2 (the input and print command) and this week
I taught Python Turtle.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building my first Telegram bot</title><link href="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/09/20/building-my-first-telegram-bot.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building my first Telegram bot" /><published>2016-09-20T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-09-20T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/09/20/building-my-first-telegram-bot</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/09/20/building-my-first-telegram-bot.html">&lt;p&gt;I built my first Telegram bot, Charge Bot. The first commit was 3 days ago (18th
September) but I first started working on it on 27th August. Then I took a three-week
break and resumed working on it on 17th September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can check the bot out on Telegram &lt;a href=&quot;https://telegram.me/charge_game_bot&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;
The Github repo is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lieuzhenghong/charge-bot/&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This checked a couple of technical firsts for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First Telegram bot&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time I used Python to write anything substantial&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First deploy on Heroku&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time using non-ASCII characters and working with UTF-8 encoding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time using a linter (pylint)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also a couple of non-technical firsts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time building a multiplayer “game”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time building anything my friends can use&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time building something for public consumption (apart from a blog)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also the first time I wrote anything for public consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I am quite happy with this project. The scope was manageable and it did
not balloon (probably because it was a game and, being a game, the scope is rather
clearly defined; what also helped was the limitations of the Telegram medium). 
At the same time, I was able to incorporate user feedback and suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-it-works&quot;&gt;How it works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Python code to write a Telegram bot is extremely trivial.
It is just a while loop that sends HTTP requests with a long timeout (long
polling). Upon receiving a response, it sends the next request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is another way which is push instead of pull (doesn’t send requests: waits for
Telegram to send updates to you) but it is far more involved and wasn’t suitable for a
first-time project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here’s the code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;get_updates&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;URL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'getUpdates?offset={0}&amp;amp;timeout={1}'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;format&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;read_offset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3600&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;requests&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;handle_updates&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. But there was a gotcha: As my background is in Javascript where all responses
are asynchronous, the line &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;req = requests.get(string)&lt;/code&gt; tripped me up. If you were to write
that in Javascript you would get &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;req == undefined&lt;/code&gt; or something like that and thus
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;handle_updates(req)&lt;/code&gt; would throw an error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Python, the synchronous nature of the code means that the assignment operator will
actually stop the evaluation until it returns a proper result. That means no callback is
needed and the code becomes very simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;snafus&quot;&gt;Snafus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;modularisation&quot;&gt;Modularisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was something that I had a lot of trouble with, despite Mark’s best efforts to help me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My code is divvied up as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;* index.py (should be main.py): is the main file, imports everything
* network.py: sends requests and handles responses
* lobby.py: code that allows players to create and join a game
* game.py: game code
* charge_keyboard.py: the inline keyboard needed for the game
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was unable to understand the idea of a function that called another function (also known
as… a callback function LOL). Here’s what I had trouble with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# network.py&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setPushDataTo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;global&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;callback&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;callback&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;func&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;pushDataToDispatcher&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;global&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;callback&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;callback&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# index.py&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;network&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;init&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&quot;&quot;Initialises the app and sets up all callbacks&quot;&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;network&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;setPushDataTo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dispatcher&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;dispatcher&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, this pattern allows a function in one file to call a function in another file,
&lt;em&gt;without importing&lt;/em&gt;. The reason why we cannot import is because we don’t want a two-way
import (index imports network, not the other way round).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we still need some way for the “child” to communicate with the “parent” and the way
to do it is by setting the callback function in the “child” to the parent’s function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not sure I am explaining it clearly…I’ll come back in a few days to this post
and see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deploying-on-heroku&quot;&gt;Deploying on Heroku&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heroku was a real pain to set up…the documentation was lacking and I spent two nights’
worth just trying to figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gist of it is that you have to have a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;requirements.txt&lt;/code&gt; file, a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Procfile&lt;/code&gt; and a
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;runtime.txt&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “Getting Started with Heroku” tutorial mentioned the first two but not the last one!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;requirements.txt&lt;/code&gt; is just a list of dependencies… that’s quite straightforward
I still don’t know what &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;runtime.txt&lt;/code&gt; does but I had to put in the line &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python-3.5.2&lt;/code&gt; in
order for Heroku to deploy my app with Python 3. I needed Python 3 because of it’s native
Unicode handling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I mean by that is: when Python2 receives a response as a string, it doesn’t actually
use Unicode encoding. In order to get it as Unicode you have to put a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;u'&lt;/code&gt; in front of it.
Python 3 does this all by itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Procfile is also not straightforward. Basically the Procfile tells Heroku what kind of
dyno your app is (web, worker, something else), what file to run with what program. So
like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;worker: python index.py --loglevel=info&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Weirdly, typing python3 index.py throws some weird error and I don’t know why and haven’t
been able to Google)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bad-code&quot;&gt;Bad code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This app was developed very haphazardly, and it shows. I used tons of global variables
because I’m very bad. Coming from a Javascript background I don’t know how to use classes,
like, &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;. So it’s good that I’m learning Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried refactoring but it was truly a huge pain and I actually had to rollback to the
previous commit because I fucked everything up. 😭&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learning-points-and-future-plans&quot;&gt;Learning points and future plans&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to make as many bots as I can in the future, because Telegram is by far the most-used
app on my phone. It was extremely smart of the Telegram team to expose this API to developers–
this has allowed it to eclipse Whatsapp even further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my next app, I will definitely try and use the webhooks push method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heroku has a free dyno tier so I have &lt;strong&gt;no idea&lt;/strong&gt; why I’m paying 8 dollars a month to DigitalOcean.
I think that I will move my automated transaction tracker over to Heroku as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned the bad code: for my next app I am going to try and write it &lt;strong&gt;right&lt;/strong&gt; and I
know everyone says that but I mean it, I’m going to aim for 0 warnings on pylint!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, this was a good learning experience, I had fun. Am pretty psyched to build my
next Telegram bot!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><summary type="html">I built my first Telegram bot, Charge Bot. The first commit was 3 days ago (18th
September) but I first started working on it on 27th August. Then I took a three-week
break and resumed working on it on 17th September.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">September</title><link href="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/09/05/september.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="September" /><published>2016-09-05T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-09-05T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/09/05/september</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/09/05/september.html">&lt;p&gt;Today I presented the WITS project to all the branch heads, including Carmo and
SMTI Comd. They said that the idea is a very good one but they were concerned
about sustainability: what will happen when I’m gone? I told them that they
could always hire me back as a consultant and that joke was rather
well-received. They were quite excited and every one of them came up with
possibilities for their branch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I didn’t win Gold, I only won silver which means I don’t get to
present, but I have to do a poster. Also we won $320… how much of that $320 is
mine will have to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This WITS project was supposed to be my ticket to recognition. I’m not sure what
chance I have now with “only” a silver. I am meeting Maj Susan on Wednesday and
I will see what she says… hopefully there’s still a chance of progressing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The iDA group has now only Rahman and me. Gabriel is trying to hang on but he
has commitment issues. Putting that aside, I’m not sure where this group is
going. Will I have to be labouring for months, years, with nothing to show for
it? We need big wins–we need to be doing something different. The idea Rahman
had is to be a &lt;em&gt;community&lt;/em&gt; that ties everyone together. That of course raises
the questions: what kind of community? and what will this community do? and I
have not been able to get a satisfactory answer from them yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My teaching the kids at Ulu Pandan is still continuing week by week but what am
I doing? The idea was to start my own Python thing but I’ve been teaching them
for so long and in any case, this is just me being subsumed into something that
others have started…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three of my projects seem to have come to a halt. I have to come up with new
ideas, new initiatives that I can push. But these three projects are sapping my
time and energy and giving me nothing in return. It is like an enormous ball and
chain is tied to me and I cannot run with all of this accumulated deadweight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some more things that I have to worry about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whether to take BMAT;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have to study for ACCA F1-F3;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn driving when?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><summary type="html">Today I presented the WITS project to all the branch heads, including Carmo and
SMTI Comd. They said that the idea is a very good one but they were concerned
about sustainability: what will happen when I’m gone? I told them that they
could always hire me back as a consultant and that joke was rather
well-received. They were quite excited and every one of them came up with
possibilities for their branch.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Long-overdue update</title><link href="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/08/11/daily-report.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Long-overdue update" /><published>2016-08-11T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-08-11T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/08/11/daily-report</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/08/11/daily-report.html">&lt;p&gt;Since the last time I posted many things have happened. We managed to go ahead
with the iDA pilot class (not entirely up to my expectations). The kids’
hackathon is now over. I am now one year older and have entered &lt;em&gt;gasp&lt;/em&gt; the
twenties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time seems to pass extremely quickly and I feel like I should be doing
more–much more–if I am to secure a scholarship. I can’t help but feel
frustrated that the things I have to do are gated by other people. I can work at
a blistering pace but if I’ve to wait for others to get back to me this limits
what I can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past few months I’ve also been doing things that I feel are not &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt;
useful with respect to getting a scholarship and part of me wonders if I should 
even bother. There are things that I have chosen to put on hold (driving) 
but there is the matter of ACCA and I’m not
sure how much effort to devote to that. It would be excellent if I can finish
F1-F3 by the end of this year but at what cost?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course hobbies such as ping-pong or 书法 and so on which I want to get
better at but am I getting anything out of it and is it sapping my time? At the 
risk of sounding like a broken record, anything that doesn’t bring me closer to
getting the scholarship I want is (by definition) unproductive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realise that not all the things I embark upon will bear fruit. (I briefly
harboured the hope that my WITS project could give me something but I am now 
convinced that the entire endeavour is otiose). But what else can I do apart
from cast the net wide and hope that something sticks?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That wasn’t a rhetorical question. I still maintain that the best way to get a
scholarship is to do one thing and do it extremely well. But what is this thing?
I am perfectly willing to devote my time and energy to
a cause as long as this cause will pop up and say, please devote your
time and energy to me and you will not be stonewalled by other people, and it
will be able to grow, and it will all be worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This futility has given me somewhat of a 野心 in the sense that I am now
unsure of what course to take. There is no doubt in my mind that Oxford is my
first choice but as the hope of getting a scholarship dwindles, I am now
considering second/third choices. I have told a friend that I intend to take the
BMAT with him and I am considering going into medicine because apparently law is
on the down and down. I am even considering going back into engineering (REP
seems quite attractive)…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I may leave modesty by the side for a while I believe I deserve a
scholarship. I think I have the drive to self-criticise and self-improve.
Largely this is borne by the deep-seated insecurity that I am simply not good
enough. I also have another advantage that others don’t: I don’t value my
personal time because I know that I am nowhere near disciplined enough to make
good use of it. Therefore, I am able to put in a lot of effort into doing
whatever the hell the organisation wants me to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is now the 11th of August and I had best start planning my after-work
timetable. Very soon I will have armoury duty to do and will (probably) not have
this luxury. For now, however, I must make full use of my time at home and not
waste it playing Hearthstone or watching Youtube videos or chatting to friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perennial feeling of not doing enough with my life has emerged yet again
and all I can do is try to salve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One year older, but just as lost.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><summary type="html">Since the last time I posted many things have happened. We managed to go ahead
with the iDA pilot class (not entirely up to my expectations). The kids’
hackathon is now over. I am now one year older and have entered gasp the
twenties.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Brexit, and the unreasonable effectiveness of demagoguery</title><link href="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/06/24/brexit.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Brexit, and the unreasonable effectiveness of demagoguery" /><published>2016-06-24T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-06-24T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/06/24/brexit</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/06/24/brexit.html">&lt;p&gt;The UK has voted to Leave, 52—48. The obvious questions are “Why did this
happen?” and What happens now?” I &lt;em&gt;won’t&lt;/em&gt; write about the consequences 
because there are many articles right now revelling in this sort of
speculation. I want to talk about the former.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was taken by surprise by the result, and from the unprecedented fall of the
pound it is obvious that the financial markets were not expecting this outcome
as well. If one were to browse the international news right before the
referandum one would have walked away with a view completely different from
reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through a campaign of misrepresentation, appeals to emotion and outright
falsehoods the Leave camp has manipulated the voting populace extremely
effectively. I’d like to talk about this “unreasonable effectiveness” and
discuss how voices of reason can reassert themselves in the realm of public
discourse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i&quot;&gt;I&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leave rallied behind the battering-ram of immigration. A coherent and consistent 
narrative was spun: joining the EU had allowed in migrants, who had come to steal jobs,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://infacts.org/mail-online-corrects-inaccurate-
nhs-migrant-story/&quot;&gt;siphon NHS funds&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/
news/article-3558818/ISIS-cells-UK-Germany-Italy-says-James-Clapper-Director-
National-Intelligence.html&quot;&gt;plant ISIS sleeper cells&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.express.co.uk/
news/uk/644855/EU-migrants-crime-Britain-deportation-migrant-crisis-free-movement-rules&quot;&gt;commit crimes with impunity&lt;/a&gt;,
and so on. Many of these articles were later ruled “significantly misleading” by the 
Independent Press Standards Organisation (IPSO); but how many read a fifty-four
word retraction tucked in a corner somewhere, and how many read the
headline of the front page?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This curation of Daily Express headlines shows very clearly the anti-immigrant
stance of the tabloids. Some gems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“You Pay For Roma Gypsy Palaces”,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Migrants Cost Britain 17Bn A Year” (migrants contribute more in taxes than they
draw in benefits)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My personal favourite: “&lt;strong&gt;The Invaders&lt;/strong&gt;” (starring Will
Smith).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://2.bp.blogspot.com/
-aYIIFTb91So/V2ULdrvWJtI/AAAAAAAABSY/5bhe2MB9-EEj4M_v3gbBJFgzupKWosyEgCLcB/s16
00/Daily%2BExpress.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Daily Express headlines&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;A selection of Daily Express headlines&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ii&quot;&gt;II&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who took him seriously when Trump announced his presidency in 2015? The man
almost seems like a comedian. “Ban all Muslims”, 
“Build a wall”, &lt;a href=&quot;https:
//twitter.com/realdonaldtrump/status/265895292191248385?lang=en&quot;&gt;global warming is a Chinese conspiracy&lt;/a&gt;. 
He holds the honour of being Politifact’s &lt;a href=&quot;http:
//www.politifact.com/personalities/donald-trump/&quot;&gt;biggest liar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/trump_on_fire.png&quot; alt=&quot;Some of Trump's claims&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;A random selection of
Trump’s latest soundbites&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely such a charlatan will not be entertained? Apparently not–he has the
Republican nomination. It remains to be seen if he will be elected President,
but it is clear that telling blatant lies can only help one’s chances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;iii&quot;&gt;III&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trump’s extremely successful campaign and the Leave vote demonstrate two
phenomena:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The “derision of the farcical”. 
We laugh at what Trump says because it’s so blatantly false it’s ridiculous,
but it’s not so obvious to the Trump supporter. 
Derision is no substitute for action; 
if we fail to correct these falsehoods we are digging our own graves.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The “unreasonable effectiveness of demagoguery”.
Despite overwhelming evidence to the contrary, the claims of Trump and the 
Leave camp have been allowed to stand, and people have been especially receptive
to their narratives.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-derision-of-the-farcical&quot;&gt;The derision of the farcical&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the GOP, Remain had underestimated the threat that was brewing because for
a long time, it seemed like populist drivel. The thought of people actually
voting for Leave was simply too ridiculous to be true. That’s why Jeremy Corbyn
felt secure enough to make this misstep:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When Jeremy Corbyn was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-politics-eu-
referendum-36506163&quot;&gt;asked&lt;/a&gt; how he rated his enthusiasm for staying in the EU out of
10, he said 7 to 7.5…[But he] needed to send a ‘clear message’ that we needed
to stay in the EU. &lt;a href=&quot;https://mainlymacro.blogspot.sg/
2016/06/defending-george-osborne-on-brexit-once.html#links&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corbyn’s answer was an honest one, but completely inadequate in a war of ideologies.
Such a statement was (predictably) pounced upon as a sign of weakness–even Corbyn isn’t
sure if he wants to stay in the EU!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Remain camp finally realised the need to “play ball” and they did what they could, 
but &lt;a href=&quot;https:
//economistsforremain.org/&quot;&gt;Economists for Remain&lt;/a&gt; was too little too late. How can a website, however
flawless its academic credentials, compete with the months–if not years–of
anti-migrant sentiment fomented by the tabloids?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://
62e528761d0685343e1c-f3d1b99a743ffa4142d9d7f1978d9686.ssl.cf2.rackcdn.com/files/
126909/area14mp/image-20160616-15079-mi76nm.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Remain versus Leave newspapers, weighted by circulation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weighted by circulation, the UK press was extremely one-sided on the issue of
Brexit. The man on the street was far more likely to walk away with the
impression that migrants from EU enact an enormous economic toll. But do
Jeremy Corbyn or David Cameron make the &lt;em&gt;Daily Mail&lt;/em&gt; a part of their daily
reading? Even if they had, would they have dismissed it out of hand?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a catastrophic failure to read the ground and Remain could have
struck back earlier, but did not do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-unreasonable-effectiveness-of-demagoguery&quot;&gt;The unreasonable effectiveness of demagoguery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bastiat’s original &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parable_of_the_broken_window&quot;&gt;parable of the broken window from &lt;em&gt;Ce qu’on voit et ce qu’on
ne voit pas&lt;/em&gt; (1850)&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Have you ever witnessed the anger of the good shopkeeper, James Goodfellow, when his careless son has happened to break a pane of glass? If you have been present at such a scene, you will most assuredly bear witness to the fact that every one of the spectators, were there even thirty of them, by common consent apparently, offered the unfortunate owner this invariable consolation – “It is an ill wind that blows nobody good. Everybody must live, and what would become of the glaziers if panes of glass were never broken?”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Now, this form of condolence contains an entire theory, which it will be well to show up in this simple case, seeing that it is precisely the same as that which, unhappily, regulates the greater part of our economical institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Suppose it cost six francs to repair the damage, and you say that the accident brings six francs to the glazier’s trade – that it encourages that trade to the amount of six francs – I grant it; I have not a word to say against it; you reason justly. The glazier comes, performs his task, receives his six francs, rubs his hands, and, in his heart, blesses the careless child. All this is that which is seen.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;But if, on the other hand, you come to the conclusion, as is too often the case, that it is a good thing to break windows, that it causes money to circulate, and that the encouragement of industry in general will be the result of it, you will oblige me to call out, “Stop there! Your theory is confined to that which is seen; &lt;strong&gt;it takes no account of that which is not seen.&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It is not seen that as our shopkeeper has spent six francs upon one thing, he cannot spend them upon another. It is not seen that if he had not had a window to replace, he would, perhaps, have replaced his old shoes, or added another book to his library. In short, he would have employed his six francs in some way, which this accident has prevented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This goes a long way in explaining the “unreasonable
effectiveness of demagoguery”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to see the migrant who takes your job. It’s easy to
see the migrant who commits a crime (it’s hard &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to see when it’s
plastered on the front page the next day). What is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; harder to see is
the lesser waiting times in the NHS, the faster recovery from the recession, the
lower tax burden on you and your children, lower prices overall…Remain had to
fight an uphill battle because of the dichotomy between &lt;strong&gt;what is seen v. what is
not.&lt;/strong&gt; Remain has lost the battle for public mindshare: the evidence
is firmly on their side, but it’s invisible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(And of course, the same is true for Trump’s campaign: 
it’s easy to see the media blitz over 
radical Islamic terrorists, the Boston bombing or the Orlando shooting, but 
not so easy to see the Muslims who contribute silently and productively to the
economy. But an article about a normal American Muslim who does normal
American things is not going to move many copies.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;v&quot;&gt;V&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-backlash-against-political-correctness&quot;&gt;The backlash against political correctness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both the US and UK there exist left- and right-wing media. I’ve just talked about
right-wing media; the conservative, sensationalist, rabidly anti-immigrant tabloids. 
It’s tempting
to think of liberal media as the bearers of truth (perhaps because everyone who
will read this lies firmly in &lt;a href=&quot;http://slatestarcodex.com/
2014/10/16/five-case-studies-on-politicization/&quot;&gt;that tribe&lt;/a&gt;), 
but of course liberal media isn’t entirely innocent, and may have dug its own
grave in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trend in liberal media today is a greater sensitivity towards minority or
marginalised groups. But too often this political correctness has been
used to silence discourse on issues that matter to the electorate. 
There is a feeling amongst the
ground that politicians have been skirting issues for fear of being bashed by
the liberal media.
The fiasco where &lt;a href=&quot;http:
//www.theguardian.com/politics/2010/apr/28/gordon-brown-bigoted-woman&quot;&gt;Gordon Brown called a woman ‘bigoted’&lt;/a&gt; lost him
the election and exemplifies the divide between the working-class and left-leaning politicians. Brown gaffed, of course–merely being concerned about immigration does not
make one a bigot–but perhaps it was a knee-jerk reaction cultivated by the
need never to appear racist at all costs. Or perhaps Brown had already bought
into the narrative that &lt;span style=&quot;font-variant: small-caps&quot;&gt;discussing
immigration’s costs is bigotry&lt;/span&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trump’s campaign so resonates with voters because of the backlash against
PC. Rightly or wrongly, the people have seen the Democrats as unwilling to
engage on the issues that matter to them (whether they &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; matter or not
is besides the point): radical Islamic terrorism and
immigration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, both left- and right-wing media have both contributed to
anti-immigrant sentiment: the left has overcorrected, 
creating a culture of shame that suppresses legitimate political discourse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vi&quot;&gt;VI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hate this article&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><summary type="html">The UK has voted to Leave, 52—48. The obvious questions are “Why did this
happen?” and What happens now?” I won’t write about the consequences 
because there are many articles right now revelling in this sort of
speculation. I want to talk about the former.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An update on my life so far</title><link href="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/05/26/daily-report.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An update on my life so far" /><published>2016-05-26T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-05-26T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/05/26/daily-report</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/05/26/daily-report.html">&lt;p&gt;These past two weeks have been uppy and downy. I had one week of zero motivation
(week 20) but after that I managed to get out of my funk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been neglecting my accounting textbook but I realise belatedly that I
don’t really have an interest in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t manage to read any books in Week 20 but I did manage to finish Bill
Bryson’s &lt;em&gt;A Short History of Nearly Everything&lt;/em&gt;. Extremely readable, extremely
fun (although rather dated–at the time of print, the Higgs boson had yet to be
discovered.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Saturday of Week 20 I managed to get two tutors after being rejected by
Marc on Friday. I met up with nauxiy and Ariel and I managed to teach them the
whole syllabus in a couple of hours each. That’s very encouraging because it
tells me that my students should have no problems handling the material. My
experience with teaching them helped me to identify several pain points and I
revamped my slides to better address these pain points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jia Run came on the Friday of Week 20 and her arrival got me out of my funk. We
ate good food and went to a couple of places although on Week 21 Monday she
asked me to go home because she wanted to shop alone :(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been writing quite a lot of Python code. I’m trying to push the limits of
what Python Turtle can do and generate the most impressive programs that will
really knock the socks off of people. My hope is that one of my tutees in the
pilot class will want to build something super cool and super ambitious and it
will be good to showcase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of pilot class–I shot a message to Oscar and he told me that the
training is likely to be in end June. So I have about a month’s time to get
everything in order. I recently revamped my syllabus and proposal, and I think
I’ll have to build a Python Titans website. (But still no idea what to put in
it)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been reading a lot of Peter Guo’s stuff (pgbovine.net). He’s an excellent
writer and he writes about things that interest me greatly (such as how to stay
singularly focused, how to get things done, computer programming and so on).
I’ll be using his tools &lt;em&gt;Codeopticon&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Python Tutor&lt;/em&gt; in my course.
&lt;em&gt;Codeopticon&lt;/em&gt; is not yet available–I found it in his research paper–I
emailed him the day before to ask him when Codeopticon would be avaiable. He
says my email “encouraged him to prioritise it”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Short-term goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build Python Titans website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continue refining proposal and syllabus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recruit another tutor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><summary type="html">These past two weeks have been uppy and downy. I had one week of zero motivation
(week 20) but after that I managed to get out of my funk.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Meeting with iDA staff (Oscar, Kiranjit and Eric)</title><link href="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/05/11/daily-report.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meeting with iDA staff (Oscar, Kiranjit and Eric)" /><published>2016-05-11T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-05-11T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/05/11/daily-report</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/05/11/daily-report.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m &lt;del&gt;on the train now on my way back to Bukit Panjang&lt;/del&gt; in BPP library. 
After this I’m going to have a meeting with Khek CO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I visited Oscar and his bunch of colleagues at iDA. I reached the office at 4pm
and Oscar came down to fetch me. The office is super nice, it really looks like
a tech company, I saw people in the basement hacking and coding and stuff. The
view is also extremely chio. I told Oscar that his office was very nice and he
told me that Google/Facebook offices are even nicer–they have hammocks and beer
taps(!!). So maybe we want to consider a career in tech. Haha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I was introduced to Oscar, Kiranjit and Eric. Oscar is this short
fat guy whose reservist unit is the same as my unit, lol (2CSH) He’s a super
nice guy, very boisterous. Keranjit is
this Indian woman who I think is the most passionate and eloquent. Eric is a
quiet guy, didn’t talk much, he used to work in education. Very
logistics-focused. He told me that he could ask companies and schools to give us
resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They complimented me on my proposal and said that I might even consider selling
my training programme syllabus to companies because it’s so good. I’m not sure 
how much of it was flattery and how much of it was genuine. But from the fact that they all
concurred it must have been pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All hubris aside, this is a learning
point. It was a good move to put so much time in the proposal because it
obviously made an impression on them which is why they were so willing to meet me.
So in the future, lesson learned–&lt;strong&gt;spend a lot of time on one’s proposal.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also learned that after I emailed Dr Balakrishnan, my email was actually 
passed around to several ministries before it finally landed in the iDA’s hands.
Glad that it finally came here–a minister’s word means a lot, evidently. Once
again, lesson learned–&lt;strong&gt;don’t be afraid to ask for what you want&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told them about Ulu Pandan Stars and they were extremely impressed. Keranjit
in particular–she was extremely happy when I told her that the underprivileged
kids actually won last year’s hackathon. Of course, I made sure to say that it
wasn’t me. But it was good to have the backing of Ulu Pandan Stars and I told
them that I was teaching them for this year’s competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were very friendly and eager to work with me. They told me that there were
a couple of other guys that had the same idea and that they wanted to form a
committee. Of course I am okay with that–even though one has to share credit,
a better outcome is better for all of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They expressed their reservations about my proposal, saying that it could be too
ambitious and too hard for first-timers with no prior programming experience.
After discussion, I finally have a &lt;em&gt;concrete plan of action.&lt;/em&gt; There is this
group called the Youth Infocomm Ambassadors (YIA) which is representatives from
secondary schools’ infocomm clubs. They told me that we could run my syllabus on
them, as a pilot test, see if the pace is OK, then iterate and improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the best part of working with the iDA is that they are extremely
powerful and well-connected. Oscar, Keranjit and Eric told me casually that they
could get a venue no problem, probably get computers from companies like Apple
and Samsung… they have the power to solve my logistics problems &lt;em&gt;just like
that&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was emphasised to me that they want this to be a &lt;em&gt;community project&lt;/em&gt;. Their
purpose is to help foster a coding community that imparts knowledge to society.
The idea is for this community to extend iDA’s current school-based initiative,
as well as teach groups not covered by the schools (e.g. working adults, seniors
and so on). They told me multiple times that they &lt;strong&gt;will&lt;/strong&gt; pull strings to get
us media coverage but they will not put iDA on it. Hence they won’t steal the
credit (their words, not mine). To me, it doesn’t matter whether iDA is on the
papers or not, but I think it matters to them. They don’t want people to think
that it’s iDA doing this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all came out of the meeting with a plan of action. My job now is
to think about my syllabus further, and &lt;strong&gt;recruit several volunteers&lt;/strong&gt;. Their
job will be to form up the committee and liaise with YIA so that we can set up
our pilot class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, an extremely useful visit and I greatly enjoyed myself. I’m
extremely optimistic on where this will go, and I loved talking to them. They
were friendly and passionate–not at all the reception I had expected from a
cold email to Dr Vivian!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;call-to-action&quot;&gt;Call to action&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whoever is reading this, please note that as of the time of writing (11th May
2016) I am looking for volunteers to teach Scratch/Python!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time commitment will not be over a few weeks. (so not one-year long, but if
the pilot programme works, then it would be great to have you on).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will train the volunteers–programming knowledge is preferred but not necessary. 
What &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; necessary is the ability to pick things up fast and the ability to 
teach others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So please ask around for me ty.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><summary type="html">I’m on the train now on my way back to Bukit Panjang in BPP library. 
After this I’m going to have a meeting with Khek CO.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Meeting with Mrs Hauw, swimming with Xiao Hui and future plans</title><link href="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/05/10/daily-report.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meeting with Mrs Hauw, swimming with Xiao Hui and future plans" /><published>2016-05-10T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-05-10T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/05/10/daily-report</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://github.com/pages/lieuzhenghong/lieuzhenghong.github.io-source/2016/05/10/daily-report.html">&lt;p&gt;The following paragraphs were written on 7th May:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I woke up at 1030 today, having slept at 2am the previous night. I was late to
the Ulu Pandan place, arriving at 1215. I met with Mrs Hauw and Dr Bimler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I got to meet Li Yicheng, Carol, Brenda, Mun Kit and I caught a glimpse of
Delphine.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Mrs Hauw explained that the 8–12 year olds were participating in a competition
called Code Xtreme or something along those lines. It’s a three-hour hackathon
where kids are supposed to use Scratch to build something that fits the theme of
FinTech.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;As expected, Mrs Hauw said that she was shorthanded and wanted me to help with
the Scratch team until July. Well, July is fine. It will serve multiple
purposes: one, it’s a probation period for Mrs Hauw to see what I can do, and
two, it’s a chance for me to learn more about pedagogical techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I hope to impress her with my consistency and willingness to work hard. Also,
I’ve been trying to build a database app for Carol, who is trying to create a
maths question repo for her kids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;swimming-with-xiao-hui&quot;&gt;Swimming with Xiao Hui&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the meetings I met up with Xiao Hui and we went swimming. She was wearing
a red sweater and I thought she looked cute in it. She is extremely
fast/I’m extremely slow (she swam 30 laps to my 26). Afterwards we went for
dinner at a prata place at J8 where she only ate two kosong prata. Then we went
to have green tea shaved ice but that’s not really my thing. Then we went to
NTUC and just walked around lol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;carols-database-app&quot;&gt;Carol’s database app&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m trying to build a database for Carol. The idea is to create a maths-question
repo, divvied up by topic. Questions are screenshots from PYPs and other
sources. The MVP DB has to contain the following features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users can upload images to the db through mobile and desktop client;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users can tag the images with metadata (autocomplete features present);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users can query questions by various criteria.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress on the database app has been extremely slow. This is because I’m having
to configure and learn many many frameworks just to get the basic stuff running.
Here’s what I have had to use/config:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node.js&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expressjs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mongodb&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multer – for file upload&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pug (Jade) – templating engine to serve up the images&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compass – just to make CSS easier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll also have to learn things like &lt;strong&gt;promises&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;async-await&lt;/strong&gt;. Right now
I’ve been struggling with the app. There is a problem where &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;res.render&lt;/code&gt; is 
being called before my manipulations are complete, which results in an empty
page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;meeting-with-ida&quot;&gt;Meeting with IDA&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Dr Balakrishnan, I’ve been able to get in touch with the iDA. Turns
out that a couple of them are already helping kids on their own time, be it
21C Girls, Mendaki, SINGA etc. I am taking off tomorrow to meet them at their office.
I’ll try and find out what they’ve been up to and how I can work with
them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><summary type="html">The following paragraphs were written on 7th May:</summary></entry></feed>
