<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-08-23T01:35:19+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">lieu’s site</title><subtitle>my personal site</subtitle><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><entry><title type="html">Aug 2017 report</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/08/22/life-report-aug-2017.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aug 2017 report" /><published>2017-08-22T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-08-22T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/08/22/life-report-aug-2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/08/22/life-report-aug-2017.html">&lt;p&gt;Since my 
&lt;a href=&quot;/2017/05/29/monthly-report-may-2017.html&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; I have done the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Went to Yunnan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dabbled in 3D printing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepared the kids for CodeXtreme 2017&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turned 21&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matriculated at NTU&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Participated in two NTU orientation camps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Withdrew from NTU&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Got IMDA’s NIS scholarship&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Built my first piece of native production software using Electron&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;went-to-yunnan&quot;&gt;Went to Yunnan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went with Samuel and Jian Kai and I had a great time. We did a lot of walking
and hiking and the 12-day trip came to about $1,200.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were very nice to me even though I don’t really know them. Mad props to
them for even letting me go on the trip with them in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved the snow-capped mountain and the hike through Tiger Leaping Gorge: took
a lot of pictures with Jian Kai’s DSLR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yulong-snow-mountain&quot;&gt;Yulong Snow Mountain&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/me.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/snow-mountain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/landscape.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tiger-leaping-gorge&quot;&gt;Tiger Leaping Gorge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/landscape-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/gorge.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/landscape-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/group-photo-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-places&quot;&gt;Other places&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/landscape-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/me-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/group-photo-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Jeff, our Dali host, I was able to watch a master calligrapher at
work, who specialises in reversed writing.
He has been practicing this for over forty years now and his writing is
critically acclaimed. We were able to get four pieces from him for free (he
usually charges); I am extremely grateful for his generosity, and to Jeff as
well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/master-at-work.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/callig.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, a great trip—thanks to Sam and JK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dabbled-in-3d-printing&quot;&gt;Dabbled in 3D printing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built a burr puzzle as a gift to Wei Heng to thank him for lending me his SUICA
card and travel adapter for my Japan trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/3d-printing/burr-puzzle-split.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;burr puzzle pieces&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/3d-printing/burr-puzzle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;burr puzzle pieces assembled&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cube in cube was just for fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/3d-printing/cube-in-cube-raw.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cube-in-cube-raw&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/3d-printing/cube-in-cube-.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cube-in-cube-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/3d-printing/cube-in-cube-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cube-in-cube-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prepared-the-kids-for-codextreme-2017&quot;&gt;Prepared the kids for CodeXtreme 2017&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The annual hackathon event. I took Audrey, Gillian and Gao Hong; Dylan was
taken by Eng Chye. Got to know Van, a final year student at NUS SoC. She helped
me greatly in the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We built a micro:bit “magic wallet” implementation, and also a little LEGO
umbrella dispenser. We demonstrated the ability to use the micro:bit to send
and receive user-specified amounts of money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/microbit-wallet/group-photo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;''&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/microbit-wallet/group-photo2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;''&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Looking glam in slippers&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/microbit-wallet/dylan-team.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;''&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/microbit-wallet/microbit-wallet-poster.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;microbit-wallet-poster&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My team took third place, and Eng Chye’s team took first. Mrs Hauw was thrilled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;turned-21&quot;&gt;Turned 21&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I treated the gang to a buffet to celebrate. The food was pretty good but Nauxiy
was so shag after his hall camp he could barely keep his eyes open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is normally where I would write about trying to be more mature and
quitting gaming and all sorts of things but this post is very very long and
besides, every year I say the same things…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/2017-birthday/2017-birthday.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;''&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marc and I will be leaving for the UK and the rest will be staying in
Singapore. I hope the six of us last long and all of us find happiness and
success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;matriculated-at-ntu&quot;&gt;Matriculated at NTU&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing to say here&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;participated-in-two-ntu-orientation-camps&quot;&gt;Participated in two NTU orientation camps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Met new people&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like the people in NTU; they are really genuine and down-to-earth. I
participated in Banyan hall camp and SCSE’s faculty orientation camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/ntu/ravenclaw.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;''&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really will miss my OG mates and I do sincerely hope that they’ll want to
keep in touch even after I go overseas to study….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;withdrew-from-ntu&quot;&gt;Withdrew from NTU&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had to be done; I had fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I plan to visit for one final week (25,26,27,28,29) and stop going after 1st
September to focus on my MOOCs and prepare for Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;got-imdas-nis-scholarship&quot;&gt;Got IMDA’s NIS scholarship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will reproduce what I wrote in May here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was rejected from both GIC and MAS in the penultimate round, the ‘group
  discussion’ round… perhaps my personality was too abrasive. Unfortunately the
  scholarship agencies don’t give feedback on unsuccessful applications.
  Nevertheless, it was a good learning experience; I don’t regret the application
  process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The last scholarship I am waiting for is IMDA. As of this moment, IMDA is
  trying to schedule an interview slot with the directors. I told them that I
  would be willing to cancel my trip to Yunnan if need be; nothing to do now but
  wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off:
Although MAS does not give feedback, I was extremely fortunate to have had Ms
Nair who did:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/scholarship/ms-nair-feedback.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ms nair's feedback&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feedback is spot-on (I predicted as much back in May) and is absolutely
something that I need to work on. Ms Nair was also kind enough to lend me some
books that will hopefully teach me not to behave like one’s on the spectrum,
including “The 5 Languages of Appreciation in the Workplace”, “Emotional
Intelligence 2.0”, “The Rules of Management” and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was interviewed by the directors who asked me (among other things) whether I
would be OK with taking PPE. The CEO also asked me, although childhood
programming education is so important, students nowadays have so many
activities vying for their time. How can we then fit programming in? I answered
that it’s exactly the wrong approach to think of programming as a separate
subject. Instead it should be worked into maths, physics, chemistry, even
literature lessons—learning Cartesian coordinates through programming a game,
or learning about circuits through wiring up a Makey-Makey, or building a
chatbot that replies only in quotes from Shakespeare’s plays. I thought the
interview went well, and I can only suppose that it did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s curious that IMDA’s entire interview process did not include an aptitude
test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a rather semantic distinction, but I am the first IMDA scholar to be
attached to IMDA. There have been many local scholars (Marvin, Wei Heng, Gui
An) and many overseas IDA/MDA scholars but due to the fact that IDA and MDA
only just merged to form IMDA, I am the first one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will work hard these three years and fight for my First in Oxford. I will
live frugally off the allowance IMDA gives me and I aim to save 300 pounds
every month to start building my nest egg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;built-my-first-piece-of-native-production-software-using-electron&quot;&gt;Built my first piece of native production software using Electron&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From July 1 to ~August 15, I built &lt;a href=&quot;www.github.com/lieuzhenghong/inspectors-gadget&quot;&gt;Inspector’s
Gadget&lt;/a&gt;, a desktop app that
streamlines the process of generating building inspection reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was at my dad’s behest, who kept on complaining about how tedious it was
to do these reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, many firsts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time using Webpack&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time using Electron&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time using Vue&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time writing a program that stored persistent data (I used localForage,
a library over indexedDB)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time writing a “native” GUI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time using GitHub’s releases feature&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time using Travis to do continuous integration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still want to learn:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to use tests and do test-driven development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A better way to package, deploy and release binaries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lieuzhenghong/inspectors-gadget/blob/master/what-i-learned.md&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
for a more comprehensive list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-plans&quot;&gt;Future plans&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have made my decision to go to Oxford and study PPE, and will not look back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goals set in May were to get a Class 3 driving license and to do at least
one machine learning project: I have not done a machine learning project by
August 2, 2017, nor will I be able to get a Class 3 driving license by 31
September 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter. I now have a new and very ambitious goal: to be accepted into Georgia Tech’s
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.omscs.gatech.edu/&quot;&gt;Online Master of Science Computer Science (OMSCS)&lt;/a&gt;
in three years’ time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote an email to the OMSCS admissions office asking “How can I make a
competitive application to OMSCS in three years’ time?” and was very pleased to
get a response back. I have only reproduced a small part of this (very
comprehensive) response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Applicants who do not meet the preferred qualifications for admission to the
OMS CS program – i.e. do not have an undergraduate degree in computer
science or related field (typically mathematics, computer engineering or
electrical engineering) AND/OR have a cumulative GPA of less than 3.0 – will
be evaluated on a case-by-case basis which includes your transcripts,
recommendation results, academic history, essays, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Having said that, in general, applicants are expected to be comfortable
programming (C or C++ are generally expected at a minimum) and to have had at
least several more advanced topics, such as Advanced OS, Networking, Theory,
and/or Algorithms. &lt;strong&gt;Usually, if the applicant does not have a CS degree, we
are looking for background that shows evidence that they have equivalent
skills (and remember an IT degree does not bring the same mix of skills as a
CS degree).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The main concern of the OMS CS Graduate Admissions Committee is
that prospective students have a competent computer science foundation. If a
prospective student feels they have sufficient work experience and/or
programming knowledge to provide this foundation (based on the OMS CS course
prerequisites), it is best to provide some sort of documentation
(recommendation letter, transcript, grade etc.) to verify their programming
skills. We also highly recommend that applicants include information
regarding relevant programming skills in their resume as well as their
application essays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We highly recommend prospective students review the prerequisites for courses
relevant to their OMS CS specialization interests and/or career interests to
determine if they have the foundation necessary to succeed in the OMS CS
program. &lt;strong&gt;If a prospective student is lacking in a certain area, we recommend
they determine which prerequisites are most critical for them to take and
then research whether or not they are available through their institution, an
accredited institution near them, or online through an accredited program
and/or MOOC from an accredited institution.&lt;/strong&gt; One useful resource may be
certified/graded MOOC’s offered through Class Central at the following
website http://www.class-central.com.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If a prospective student does pursue some prerequisite courses, we would
expect to see some sort of grade as part of the evaluation from the course
(some courses show a grade or percentile, others do not do any evaluation and
will not show their CS knowledge-base). &lt;strong&gt;Please note, completing coursework at
an accredited institution is recommended. Additionally, if you do take
prerequisite courses, it will likely strengthen your application more to have
prerequisite courses completed when you apply as grades verify you have
obtained the necessary skills to succeed in a graduate level CS program.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I have decided to dedicate the next three years to study the
equivalent of an undergraduate CS syllabus on my own, while studying
PPE at Oxford. I hear from my friends and OUMSSA “parents” that the workload
even for PPE is not too bad, but we’ll soon see. Securing a First of course
comes &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; but I believe that by paring the inefficiencies out of my life I
will be able to accomplish these two goals with aplomb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being an IMDA scholar could help me achieve these goals more easily. I won’t
have to waste my time looking for a job or an internship; I will (hopefully) be
given $3,000 to help finance the cost of attaining these certificates under
NIS’s Talent Development Programme; they will give me a 1 year—1.5 year
deferment before I start serving my bond at IMDA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tentatively, I will be following the syllabus outlined in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/open-source-society/computer-science&quot;&gt;Open Source
Society University’s CS
curriculum&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a
long road and I will need to start formally planning out my study roadmap very
soon, perhaps by the end of this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grind never ends—not after my As, not during army, not even after I have
gotten my scholarship. But I am beginning to realise that I may like and even
need this grind in my life more than I think I do.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="progress report" /><summary type="html">Since my last post I have done the following:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building a Raspberry Pi console</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/30/building-a-raspberry-pi-console.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building a Raspberry Pi console" /><published>2017-05-30T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-05-30T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/05/30/building-a-raspberry-pi-console</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/30/building-a-raspberry-pi-console.html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, Bailin and I finished the build of the Raspberry Pi console.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Raspberry Pi console project is the culmination of more than half a year of
effort. For the last eight months, I have been teaching the kids at Ulu Pandan
Stars Python (specifically Python Turtle). After much hand-holding and patient
instruction the kids were able to write the code for a Pong clone (mostly) all
by themselves. (We wrote the code that read from the GPIO pins).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kids don’t understand all the concepts, however, which makes me think that
the project is a little too ambitious. For example, they have no idea what the
ADC does, how the wiring in the Raspberry Pi works and/or how the Raspi reads
the hardware inputs. I don’t see this as &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; big a deal, though, because even
if they don’t understand it, at least they know about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, the kids definitely &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; understand a lot of things: basic
programming concepts (functions, loops, conditionals), Cartesian coordinates,
event-based programming, and so on. We have also been training them to talk
about what they have done (the girls lack the confidence to speak in a formal
setting) but there’s still a lot of work that still needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;parts-used&quot;&gt;Parts used&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7-inch touchscreen LCD: 118 SGD&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Raspberry Pi 3: ~65 SGD&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rheostats, 2: ~2 SGD each&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;60mm buttons, 2: 4.50 SGD each&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;45mm buttons, 2: 3.50 SGD each&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ADC, 3 (but we used only 1): ~7 SGD each&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Box file from Popular: ~5 SGD&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;X-acto knife: 13 SGD&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solder iron: given to me by Snoopy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total cost: ~250 SGD&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-draft&quot;&gt;First draft&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project started as a ‘shoebox console’ but we found that a shoebox was way
too flimsy. Here’s what that looked like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/old_console_closeup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/old_console_closeup2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/old_console_students.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
Zhengyang with the students&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;video width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/old_console_video&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video of me pressing the buttons&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used an X-acto knife to cut the holes in the box and had to solder wires
onto the rheostats and the push buttons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;improved-version&quot;&gt;Improved version&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bailin was able to buy a box file from Popular for $5 so we used that instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_wip_soldering.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Soldering the buttons&quot; /&gt;
Bailin soldering the buttons. His hands were shaky so I took over for the more
delicate parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_wip.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Work-in-progress console&quot; /&gt;
The box before we put all the stuff inside it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_wip_closeup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Closeup of the work-in-progress console&quot; /&gt;
Closeup of the WIP console; power bank not pictured&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_video&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video tour of the console&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_side.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Console from the side&quot; /&gt;
Side view&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_closeup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Closeup of the console&quot; /&gt;
Closeup of the console&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_gaming_video&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mom and my cousin playing with it: the game is buggy and I will get
Audrey and Gillian to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finishing-up&quot;&gt;Finishing up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I called for an extra lesson where I got the kids to mount the final two
buttons so they couldclaim to have done at least some of it themselves (instead
of having the tutors do all the work). Here’s what the final version looks like
now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_v2_front.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Console from the front&quot; /&gt;
Front view&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_v2_34.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Console from the side&quot; /&gt;
3/4-view. I think it &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareidolia&quot;&gt;kind of looks like a
face!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_v2_closeup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Closeup of the console&quot; /&gt;
Closeup of the console&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually I still don’t know how the thing is wired because Zheng Yang did the
lion’s share of the work in wiring. I’ll have to learn from Bailin how
everything is wired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my first time working with a Raspberry Pi as well as hardware
components like rheostats and buttons: my previous projects were all
software-only. I’m very grateful to Zheng Yang and Bailin for helping so much
(it literally could not have been done without Zheng Yang).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kids will finish their DSA exercise in August. Whether or not they get into
DSA is out of my control but I hope that they will have the confidence and
motivation to pursue similar projects in the future. STEM is the future, after
all…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kids should patch their games and do some bug-fixing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to build a few ‘demonstration games’ on the console that make
good use of the two rheostats (an interesting input medium).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s my hope that this console can be used as a springboard for future
programming lessons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="programming" /><category term="build" /><category term="making" /><category term="programming-education" /><summary type="html">Yesterday, Bailin and I finished the build of the Raspberry Pi console.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">May 2017 report</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/29/monthly-report-may-2017.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="May 2017 report" /><published>2017-05-29T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-05-29T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/05/29/monthly-report-may-2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/29/monthly-report-may-2017.html">&lt;p&gt;Since my 
&lt;a href=&quot;/2017/03/31/quarterly-report-2017.html&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; I have done the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finished my internship at iGlobe (ended May 12, 2017)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Been rejected by MAS and GIC in the penultimate round&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Went to Japan for the first time in my life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finished building the Raspberry Pi console&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finished my first substantial MOOC, Andrew Ng’s Machine Learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Built my first executable file (.exe rather than .py) and wrote &lt;em&gt;software&lt;/em&gt; rather than a &lt;em&gt;program&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these deserve a separate post so I’ll dedicate the whole of today to writing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finished-my-internship-at-iglobe&quot;&gt;Finished my internship at iGlobe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started interning at iGlobe on 23rd January 2017 and ended 12th May 2017. My
main responsibility was to help the investment team (Jeff) in his sourcing for
new deals. That means that I accompanied him to meetings with promising
startups and wrote minutes for the meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a later stage, this evolved into due diligence whereby I had to research on
the company to see if i) they could deliver on their promised claim; ii) they
did not misrepresent the uniqueness or impact of their technology; iii) there
were any other competitors in this market and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the final stage, I was tasked to help write &lt;strong&gt;investment papers&lt;/strong&gt; for the
company. Investment papers are papers written by the investment team for the
Board. They introduce the company and explain why the company is worth
investing in. I helped Jeff do in-depth research in the technology of the
company and wrote those sections of the investment paper. Over the course of my
internship I helped write investment papers for V-key, an online crpyto company
and SourceSage, an app for oleochemical traders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also tasked to do market research on industries iGlobe was interested in
(e.g. insurtech, fintech, blockchain). I produced three research reports on
insurtech, medtech and payment data monetisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the investor side, I helped the investor team conduct research on the
possibility of getting family offices to invest in iGlobe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also learned miscellaneous administrative stuff like how to use a courier
service, how to post a letter and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;programming-at-iglobe&quot;&gt;Programming at iGlobe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote two programs during my stint at iGlobe,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lieuzhenghong/form-letterer&quot;&gt;form-letterer&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lieuzhenghong/form-emailer&quot;&gt;form-emailer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These programs make it easy to send multiple similar emails (form emails) to
different recipients. As an intern, I was given drudgery like this to do and I
didn’t like it (I am a very lazy person). Therefore, I wrote these programs to
help me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Form Letterer takes in a specially-formatted Word document and a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.csv&lt;/code&gt; data
file, and returns multiple personalised Word documents. This is useful if you
want to be printing contracts for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Form Emailer automatically sends personalised emails to receipients, and
supports attachments as well. It can be used in conjuction with Form Letterer
to send each recipient a different Word document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These programs are actually quite trivial (form-letterer was actually harder
because of how difficult it is to manipulate Word documents programmatically!).
It was yet another example of, as Mark puts it, “library whacking”. However, I
still learned a lot from these projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I learned how to write code that is meant for the end-user. This
means catching exceptiosn and throwing ‘friendly’ error messages; being
permissive and clever when handling imperfect user input; building an
executable instead of leaving it as a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;program.py&lt;/code&gt; file (may write a separate
post on this); writing comprehensive and easy-to-read documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second of all, I learned how to use Python’s &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;argparse&lt;/code&gt; to write a command-line
program! I’ve never done this before and I’m very happy with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also happy with the fact that my code is clean and follows PEP-8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m slightly regretful that I didn’t manage to write a nice TUI/GUI. Instead I
used Python’s &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;input&lt;/code&gt; to prompt users to fill in their details instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the real test of any piece of software is: is it being used? And I
am happy to report that it is (for now…). I met Kim and her nephew at a calligraphy
competition yesterday and she told me that they successfully used it to send
their quarterly report without any help on my part!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I am very pleased to have written a piece of software that is
successfully being used by end-users. I’m also happy that I was able to
contribute to iGlobe above and beyond the help normally expected from an
intern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rejected-from-scholarships&quot;&gt;Rejected from scholarships&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was rejected from both GIC and MAS in the penultimate round, the ‘group
discussion’ round… perhaps my personality was too abrasive. Unfortunately the
scholarship agencies don’t give feedback on unsuccessful applications.
Nevertheless, it was a good learning experience; I don’t regret the application
process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last scholarship I am waiting for is IMDA. As of this moment, IMDA is
trying to schedule an interview slot with the directors. I told them that I
would be willing to cancel my trip to Yunnan if need be; nothing to do now but
wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-plans&quot;&gt;Future plans&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The path ahead of me is bifurcated. All depends on my decision to go to Ox or
NTU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are things that I will be doing no matter my eventual choice, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-very-clear-goals&quot;&gt;Some very clear goals:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get a Class 3 driving license by September 31 2017&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do at least one machine learning project by August 2 2017&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-more-nebulous-ones&quot;&gt;Some more nebulous ones:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think about a new niche for the Codellective: see &lt;a href=&quot;http://saturdaykids.com/creative-coder/pykids-level-1/&quot;&gt;this Saturday kids
class&lt;/a&gt; also doing
Python Turtle idea but they have a lot of traction and are charging 700-900
per workshop?? I think the real question is : what is Codellective, what are
we doing different from the rest, what kind of volunteers do we want?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pipe-dreams&quot;&gt;Pipe dreams:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pretty sure that these won’t happen&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn to play one of Faye Wong’s songs on the piano by 2nd Aug 2017—no point
asking Prof Chiu for the scores if I never use them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of a way to earn some money during university&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="progress report" /><summary type="html">Since my last post I have done the following:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2017 Quarterly Report I</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/03/31/quarterly-report-2017.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2017 Quarterly Report I" /><published>2017-03-31T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-03-31T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/03/31/quarterly-report-2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/03/31/quarterly-report-2017.html">&lt;p&gt;Wah. Really in a blink of an eye 3 months can pass just like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what have I been doing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In January I went on a trip to Cebu with my JC class. For only 1018 dollars I managed to get a diving license (although the license has yet to arrive after two months). It was a very good 9-day (or was it 8 days?) trip where I had nice food and got to try foods like Balut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diving was a really good experience and I want to go again, I will probably want to invest in a mask with prescription though because I couldn’t see shit until the sardine run dive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realised that traveling with a big group is not easy because different people have different wants. Nonetheless, the trip went relatively smoothly and I felt that I got closer with a few people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On January 23 I started the internship at iGlobe.
I think there is room for me to do more work.
This week will be the 2-month mark at iGlobe. I have been fortunate enough to be able to sit in for many meetings with investees and am learning a lot about different startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently working on a form letterer for iGlobe. Unfortunately, I predict that the uptake will be quite minimal. 
I’m not sure. Have to make it as easy to use as possible because the biggest obstacle to adoption is simply user laziness.
&lt;strong&gt;Update 31st March&lt;/strong&gt; Finished building the app and I may write a post about it. We’ll see. I’m the only one using it now&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February, I started on Andrew Ng’s Machine Learning MOOC. Have finished about 3/4th of it right now, and aim to revisit it soon…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;March was scholarship season and I have put the MOOCs on hold. I plan to resume in April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;scholarship-overview&quot;&gt;Scholarship overview&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;current-progress&quot;&gt;Current progress:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JTC: Rejected&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MAS: 2/4&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GIC: 2/4&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CAAS: 0/4 (went for first round, now waiting for result)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IMDA, PSC, EDB: Pending (not heard from them)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IE: forgot about it tbh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mas-scholarship&quot;&gt;MAS Scholarship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went for the first round of the MAS scholarship where we were tasked to write an essay about the two things I would change about Singapore and why. Then I had to take a psychometric test which was easy-peasy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have just came back from the second round of interview from MAS. I’m not sure if I will hear back from them. (Update 30 Mar: I did, third round is on Monday, 3 Apr)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the interview, I got to talk with a HR rep, Henry. Henry said that there were about 600+ applicants this year. They chose 150 for the first round. Out of those 100, 30-40 are in this secondround. When the fourth round begins, there are about eight candidatesand they will finally award the scholarship to 4-6 candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He confirmed that some years MAS does award 0 or 1 scholarships and in the distant past, more than 10 years ago, they awarded 10+ scholarships. The range nowadays is 4-6 though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is evidently a very selective process. Even now, I have only a 10%of getting the scholarship if we look at the numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the interviewers asked if I had any questions for them I asked for their feedback on my preformance and what I could do to improve. They were quite taken aback by this question and one person commented that I was the first to ask them that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interviewer said that she liked my candour because when they first asked me why MAS I just said that if I don’t get a scholarship I can’t go to Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two interviewers commented that in the future I should come prepared with an example of an MAS policy and be ready to defend it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HR person said that my mind spin too fast and my mouth cannot catch up. Sometimes I will leave the thread of one argument hanging and jump to the next one. And spoke too fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were the suggestions they had for improvement. I will definitely prepare more for future interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of them did say it’s obvious that I have a bright future and to keep in touch even if I don’t get the scholarship. (He quickly clarified that this does not impute anything about whether I had gotten the scholarship). But I’m pretty sure that this is something they say to every single candidate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I think I made a pretty unique impression (whether it was a &lt;strong&gt;good&lt;/strong&gt; impression is something else entirely). It could have gone better. It was a long interview though, one hour long, and my legs were shaking at the end of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;jtc-scholarship-short-and-perfunctory&quot;&gt;JTC scholarship: short and perfunctory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JTC scholarship interview was a group interview with 3 members of HR. They asked us rather silly questions like “what do you think of cyberbullying” and I was like diao… come and ask this kind of question…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it was quite funny when they asked us what scholarship we are applying for/ what scholarships we want to apply for and all of us basically just listed out macam shopping list like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They rejected me very swiftly—the evening of the interview, in fact—and at the risk of sounding sour grapes, I don’t think JTC would have been right for me, either. So no great loss there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It didn’t take much courage but I was able to get numbers of my fellow scholarship applicants, Jerry, Engracia and Jazreel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to talk about this right now but I think there is a fine line between pushing and jioing. It’s important to walk this line right and sometimes it may be easy to overstep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;caas-scholarship&quot;&gt;CAAS scholarship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met Bryce at the CAAS scholarship. CAAS scholarship was pretty fun, I liked it a lot. We weretasked to roleplay as civil servants of CAAS and there were two parts. First part was a debate on proposed legislature regulating drones and the other part was&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gic&quot;&gt;GIC&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 28th of March I went for the GIC interview. It was great that Mrs Hauw introduced me to Phionna who was able to allay somewhat my anxiety regarding the interview. I was interviewed by two people who were Yen Chen and… someone else I unfortunately forgot the name of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They asked me why I chose PPE given my interest in tech, about my work in iGlobe and similar questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also asked me three rather pointed questions. First, they asked to tell them about the greatest risk I have ever taken, to which I answered my choice to take ELL instead of Econs inJ1. Then they asked me about a time where I failed and I told them about my NS experience. Lastly, they asked what my greatest weakness was (I joked with them that my greatest weakness is that I’m too long winded, interviewers always tell me to hurry up) and I answered that I can be too blunt and I can be too honest. I volunteered my Malay Special Program experience&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The common comment was that they really appreciated my candiness/candour but they were still uncertain whether i was 100% into the job itself. At MAS they were worried about whether I would be able to do the drudgery and at GIC they said that the work at iGlobe doesn’t necessarily reflect the work I will be doing at GIC, which will be more spreadsheets and stuff and less startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;other-stuff&quot;&gt;Other stuff&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marc has really changed a lot after going for his internship. Among other things he has taught me about the importance of being assertive and charismatic. We made a promise to each other to seize oppportunities for daygame, really talk to other people, I have been trying to do so but not entirely successfully. I did miss out yesterday at the gym, there was a pretty girl and I didn’t get to talk to her although I wanted to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been making some gains in the gym but it’s predominately bench gains because God knows it’s the only lift I program properly… it’s harder to progress with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m glad that plans for going on a trip with the 6 offenders are finally in the works. We have bought the tickets and Nauxiy and I have planned a more-or-less fixed itinerary.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="progress report" /><summary type="html">Wah. Really in a blink of an eye 3 months can pass just like that.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2016</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/27/2016-in-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2016" /><published>2016-12-27T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-12-27T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2016/12/27/2016-in-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/27/2016-in-review.html">&lt;p&gt;2016 has been a long year and it’s hard to keep track of all the things I’ve
done. I started this blog (I think it’s more of a diary really) for the express
purpose of keeping track of what I have been doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;calendar-of-events-2016&quot;&gt;Calendar of events 2016&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This diary/blog has been a great help in remembering the things that I’ve done
this past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Month&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;What I did&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Jan&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;Nothing of note&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Feb&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;Nothing of note&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Mar&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;Nothing of note&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Apr&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Started this blog, approached IDA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;May&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Started teaching at Ulu Pandan Stars&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Jun&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Ran a pilot course of Python Titans at IDA.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Jul&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Started work on the WITS project (Automated transaction tracker)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Aug&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Continued working on WITS project, started Co{de}llective&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Sep&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Finished WITS project, Built Charge Bot&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Oct&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Started on MOOCs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Nov&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Started building CodeGL (CPU visualisation)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Dec&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Holiday with family, built Co{de}llective website&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-i-have-succeeded-at&quot;&gt;Things I have succeeded at&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gaining-programming-skill&quot;&gt;Gaining programming skill&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I’ve focused on improving my technical skill. I feel that I have
learned a lot but there’s still a billion things to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My focus this year has been on the Web and I don’t think that’s a bad thing &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt;
because the Web is so ubiquitous after all. However,
after taking CS50 and doing some C, I realise that it can be a lot of fun. I
think I want to move away from building websites as it has become somewhat trivial
with the advent of excellent front-end frameworks like Bootstrap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still enjoy
game and app development and am likely to continue pursuing it in the future but 
after dipping my toes in CS50 I think I would like to explore the more technical/
computer science aspect of development. That means ML/NN/AI/compilers? instead
of web development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will run through this year’s projects each in chronological order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;this-blog&quot;&gt;This blog&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it is&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-explanatory&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Github Pages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jekyll,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buying a domain name&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Configuring DNS settings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first technical project of 2016. Building a website was not new to me but
using frameworks and build tools to build a website was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the longest time my approach to building a site was to whack &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt;
and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;style.css&lt;/code&gt; files (have been doing it since Sec One), and they’ve never been
hosted under a custom domain name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;automated-transaction-tracker&quot;&gt;Automated transaction tracker&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it is&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An app built during NS for WITS made to solve the problem of overdue
loans. It is basically a digital 12-11 record/digital loan book that
tracks who made what loans and sends SMS messages to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system supports user auth and multiple stores. Supervisors can
create stores and invite storemen users to contribute to that store.
Only invited users can see and modify transactions of a store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I built a front-end UI for users to access through their phones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately nobody wanted to use it as it was simply
extra work (but I still got Silver).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building a REST app&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;React&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ExpressJS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MongoDB and Mongoose&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deploying on DigitalOcean&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Twilio API and how to send SMSes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;User authentication (token-based)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JSON Web Tokens (JWT)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hashing and salting passwords&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;General back-end concepts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the largest project of 2016! It was an extremely ambitious and extremely
tiring project. I had a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of trouble with it although now, looking back, it
seems pretty trivial. (More on this phenomenon next time.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing all the Express routers/routes was hard, the MongoDB database queries
even harder, and the React UI hardest of all! It was this project that made me
realise that back-end is actually not hard and much more fun than the front-end.
This was a watershed moment as previously the back-end was something extremely
mysterious and inaccessible to me; I remember in 2015 I had no idea what Dae Koon
was doing when we were doing the Smart Gallery app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;charge-bot&quot;&gt;Charge Bot&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it is&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A telegram bot that allows two players to play the childhood game of
Charge. It is basically a while loop running on a Heroku instance
that long polls the Telegram server for updates. (it is not a server,
it is a client)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Telegram Bot API&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Long polling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More REST practice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deploying on Heroku&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I built this simple Telegram bot a couple months after the Bot API was released.
The moment the Bot API was announced CKY and I immediately discussed building a 
bot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An extremely simple Telegram bot that took a deceptively long time to do. 
I must admit that the concept
of long polling gave me a lot of grief: I had initially implemented my long polling
function recursively but that caused a stack overflow after some time. (Can you
figure out how to write a long polling function in a non-recursive manner?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;codegl-or-a-failed-shenzhen-io-knockoff&quot;&gt;CodeGL, or a failed Shenzhen I/O knockoff&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it is&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A “game” that allows you to input assembler commands into an extremely
rudimentary text box.
These commands are fed into a virtual machine (built by Mark) and
run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I built a display showing the values of the 16 32-bit registers
so you can draw very rudimentary images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently working on a display for RAM as well as extending the
parser/language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;C++&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SDL&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minimal knowledge of how a CPU works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this incomplete project has not been touched for more than a month, I 
learned a lot from it. It was my first time writing C++ code and my first time doing anything
graphics library related (I used SDL). I was quite happy to actually be writing a
graphical application because I always had this impression that writing graphics
stuff was incredibly difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, it would have been incredibly difficult had I not taken the CS50 course,
which introduced me to C. Otherwise I’m sorry to say that the unfamiliar syntax
would have scared me off (not to mention &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;make&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cmake&lt;/code&gt;!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-i-have-failed-at&quot;&gt;Things I have failed at&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;going-to-the-gym-consistently&quot;&gt;Going to the gym consistently&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have made gains, but I could have made more had I been more disciplined and
less lazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Am still looking into a routine for 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;acca&quot;&gt;ACCA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a 500 dollar course with Marc and realised that 
a) accountancy is not for
me and 
b) my interest and comparative advantage lies elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I have decided to abandon this track indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Marc (or rather Marc’s dad) told me that an ACCA qualification is useful
for going into finance into the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;swimming-15km&quot;&gt;Swimming 1.5km&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After getting a couple of bad sunburns and falling sick I stopped swimming with
Wei Liang. I can swim freestyle much more comfortably than I could before I started
swimming this year but my stroke is still poor and there’s a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not like swimming in public pools because they are crowded and gross.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I will pick this up in the future as a hobby and to get tan but I don’t
foresee swimming becoming a part of my life anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learning-to-drive&quot;&gt;Learning to drive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did not learn to drive. I had better things to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will definitely have to learn sooner or
later… am thinking of learning it in May after my internship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-that-are-neither-here-nor-there&quot;&gt;Things that are neither here nor there&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reading-50-books-in-a-year&quot;&gt;Reading 50 books in a year&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have actually succeeded in this endeavour (47 books–close enough) but I am 
parking this here as I do not feel
that this was a good use of my time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong – I love books – but I didn’t feel like I really got anything
from them. Because&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For skills like programming, reading books is not as useful
as doing and reading articles/code examples online. There are of course excellent
books like the Gang of Four’s 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Design_Patterns&quot;&gt;Design Patterns&lt;/a&gt; or JS: The Good Parts
but 
these books are meant more as
reference guides, so in what sense can you say to have “finished” them?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Low retention. Looking at the book list I kept for this entire year,
I realise that I have forgotten most of the content of the books. I did not use 
to have this problem because I would reread books again and again until I had 
internalised completely the concepts of the books. But this year, in an effort to
hit the completely arbitrary number 50 (and also because I like buying new books),
I did not do this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Is there anything that can be done to remedy this? I read that you are not 
 supposed to read non-fiction books the same way you read fiction books – that
 is, from cover to cover, page 1 to end. Instead you should selectively skim
 the book for information and actively summarise/take notes while reading. I
 did not do this and do not like doing this largely because it feels too much
 like &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt; but I may have to give this method a try in the future. I did
 make some attempt at taking down notes but they were largely perfunctory and
 shit.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;teaching-at-ulu-pandan-stars&quot;&gt;Teaching at Ulu Pandan Stars&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truth be told, I did not very much enjoy the front part of teaching where I was
preparing them for the CodeXtreme hackathon. Many of the kids were simply not able
to learn any substantial programming concepts. I became much happier and far more
excited when I was able to pull out the four kids and try out my own curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that we have a clear goal for the kids – prepping them for DSA – is 
also extremely motivating. I am an extremely goal-oriented person and it helps me
greatly in my week-to-week planning if I have something in the future to look 
forward to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have filed this under “neither here nor there” because although the kids have 
already learned a lot, I have not delivered results yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;co-founding-codellective&quot;&gt;Co-founding Co{de}llective&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will reserve judgement/comment on this as it’s too early to say anything about
it right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;areas-for-improvement&quot;&gt;Areas for improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-management&quot;&gt;Time management&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that I did a lot of things this year but not very efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have improved greatly in that I do not slack off as much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is another subtle time-wasting bad habit I am guilty of and that is
my constant multitasking on the computer. It’s much more insidious because you 
think that you’re being productive and doing a lot of work but in reality you
haven’t established the Csikszentmihalyi-an “flow state” or “deep work” or
“intense focus” or whatever you want to call it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have had extremely occasional states whereby I was completely focused on the
task, be it reading a book or writing blog posts/code. 
Code is a little bit harder because it
necessitates a lot of SO and asking people for hep and that inherently breaks 
one’s rhythm. But there is no excuse for reading a book because I frequently got
distracted by small things like looking a word up on Pleco only to start replying
to Telegram messages, then going on Reddit… and even if the distraction lasts
only a few seconds, the flow state has been broken and productivity takes a 
nosedive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;completionist-streak&quot;&gt;Completionist streak&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to finish what you started and don’t be bantuerfei
but I have found that such one-dimensional thinking is not entirely
accurate either. Yes, I used to have (and still do have) the problem
of starting things or having goals and then not completing them. I 
identified this tendency early and made it my goal to drive this habit
out of my life by any means possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I realised after talking with Mark and reading some stuff online
like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pgbovine.net&quot;&gt;Prof Guo&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://freakonomics.com/podcast/new-freakonomics-radio-podcast-the-upside-of-quitting/&quot;&gt;this Freakonomics podcast&lt;/a&gt;
that a single-minded focus on trying to complete something that’s honestly
not worth your time is actually counterproductive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was doing the course CS50 I complained to Mark that although the front few
lessons were very educational, the later webdev lessons were not as they covered
ground that I already know. Mark told me that there’s no need to finish the course,
just like there’s no need to finish reading books or textbooks. The most important
thing is to get the information and learn as much as you can from the resource; 
it isn’t important at all if you “finish” it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I have had a change in thinking and am no longer adamant about finishing the
CS50 course. However, I will still do Problem Set 8 and the Final project because
I think those two problem sets are educational for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the challenge is in being able to identify which goals are not worth
pursuing or completing because I don’t learn from them, 
and which goals I don’t &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; like completing because they
are boring, difficult or hard to measure progress toward. It’s still 
very important to be able to “finish strong” (Prof Guo’s words,
not mine), of course, and this grit is a quality that I have to continue to cultivate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am happy with the way 2016 went. I have been productive and I have achieved the
goals I care most about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also just as important is the fact that I have tried new things and quit them 
when I realised that I did not care about them at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the risk of this blog post sounding like an Oscar acceptance speech:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am
extremely grateful to Mark, without whom all the aforementioned technical projects 
would be impossible to complete. He has gotten me unstuck more times than I can count
and possesses an incredible patience for putting up with my incessant questions.
Also, for hosting me at his house many times.
(The same goes for Wei Heng, minus the hosting me at his house part).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to CKY for being my best friend and being the only person I can 
bounce my silly game design/writing/business ideas off of. I also admire him greatly for
being extremely prolific and driven in his field of game design and development
and I hope that some of that productivity will rub off on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ariel has helped me a lot as an enthusiastic and responsive sounding-board for
my ideas. More than anyone else I have shared with her my ideas and concerns
about the Co{de}llective and Python Titans projects and she has always given me
good advice and honest feedback. She also spent two weekends of her time to 
help me run the nerve-wracking pilot program at IDA (on extremely short notice,
no less). I cannot thank her enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have Ming Shi to thank for introducing me to Ulu Pandan Stars and Mrs Hauw and
I owe him a meal. And speaking of Mrs Hauw, I must also be grateful to her for
giving me so much free rein with the C4C P5 class and for giving me the opportunity
to intern at her company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Sean, for helping me do my WITS poster despite his NS commitments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have thanked all these people for their contribution to my goals but I’d also
like to point out that I enjoy their company greatly and am grateful for that, too.
To that end, I’d like to thank all of my friends for being patient 
with my flaws, honest with their feedback, and liberal with their company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s to 2017!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="annual review" /><category term="progress report" /><summary type="html">2016 has been a long year and it’s hard to keep track of all the things I’ve done. I started this blog (I think it’s more of a diary really) for the express purpose of keeping track of what I have been doing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2015</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/26/2015-in-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2015" /><published>2016-12-26T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-12-26T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2016/12/26/2015-in-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/26/2015-in-review.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I wrote this last year in a Google Doc before this blog existed. I think before
I go about writing 2016’s Year in Review I should post this one, for completeness.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2015 has come to an end and I think it’s a good idea to write down the big things that have transpired this year and what I can look forward to in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year was the transition from student to NSF and the transition has not been entirely pleasant. Although I’m quite pleased with my current vocation and job scope I have a slipped disc and a fucked-up wrist to show for my troubles. I did not have a good time in BMT but I have met some new acquaintances and we meet up occasionally. I’m on OK terms with my colleagues at work as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other large event was of course  my trip to Oxford and I think this was the highlight of the year in terms of personal growth. I think it gave me a real new perspective with regard to interpersonal relationships and it got me out of my rut as well. It wasn’t the trip per se that was really helpful as much as it was the months of reading books and writing notes. It made the wait in army more bearable, I learned a lot, and i think that I should continue with this attitude of learning in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the things I think I did quite well in 2015 were the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did well in creating a budget and meticulously documenting my spending, and am accurate to the dollar. I will be improving the spreadsheet in 2016 by tracking my spending by category (the abortive attempt to create the Pennywise budgeting app has been shelved indefinitely) and using some graphs as well which will be quite cool hehe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did well in reading a lot of books in preparation for Oxford and although I don’t have anything to prepare for anymore I have set a goal of reading 48 books this year - that’s four books a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t do so well in the realm of interpersonal relationships. I guess part of this is inevitable because all my close friends are splitting up and going for NS and of course the girls are going to uni and all that. I don’t feel like I’m that close with my colleagues in the workplace either. And of course I’m still single but I’m honestly not that bothered despite all the noise I make about it because (i) my previous experience has made me realise that it’s hard to find a partner who shares a lot of my values and (ii) I should concentrate on self-improvement rather than chasing tail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of which, 20 is a significant milestone. It should be a portent of greater maturity now that I’ve crossed over into adulthood. Every year I tell myself that I should play less computer games and it never happens… because my friends are very bad influences…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="annual review" /><category term="progress report" /><category term="goal setting" /><summary type="html">I wrote this last year in a Google Doc before this blog existed. I think before I go about writing 2016’s Year in Review I should post this one, for completeness.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ORD lo</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/06/ORD-lo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ORD lo" /><published>2016-12-06T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-12-06T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2016/12/06/ORD-lo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/06/ORD-lo.html">&lt;p&gt;these two chrysalid years are finally over:
this is a period of unprecedented freedom and it’s imperative i &lt;strong&gt;don’t waste my time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the month of November it was a huge rut for me– didn’t get any work done, any
project finished or finish reading any book and this is really unacceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest problem is that I am &lt;strong&gt;waking up too late&lt;/strong&gt;. This really harshes my
vibe because I usually wake up at 10am/11am and it’s this no-man’s-land kind of
timing whereby I convince myself to makan first before going gym but by then
it’s so late and i drag drag drag… case in point, it’s &lt;del&gt;3pm&lt;/del&gt; 4pm now and I still
haven’t moved my fucking ass to the gym yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to correct my sleeping schedule so that I am sleeping at midnight and waking up 9am latest. This will allow me to make 10am gym which is just nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-ive-to-do-in-december&quot;&gt;What I’ve to do in December&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be travelling from 11th to 24th so somehow need to find opportunities to work out.
And to complete the rest of my projects as stated below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Catch up to the original plan of 52 books (give myself discount la, 50 will do…)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Currently: 43 books which means&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;7 books in 4 weeks: that’s roughly two books a week which is
honestly doable&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;current book (Tuesday: a fanti 36ji book: to finish by this week,
  I have to finish 6 jis a day). then it’s 2 books a week henceforth&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finish CS50!!! This is a MUST:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Problem Set 6 – can be done in a day&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Problem Set 7 – ditto&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Problem Set 8 – a little bit more involved&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Final project: currently working on the opengl CPU as a just-for-fun final project.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get the Co{de}llective site up and running
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Kay has already almost finished with the design so it’s up to me now to translate it into reality&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cut to 67kg bodyweight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plans-for-january&quot;&gt;Plans for January&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From 4th–14th Jan I will be overseas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then I start my internship on the 23rd and that will last for 3–4 months.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And I can’t forget to get my stuff ready to apply for scholarships/internships&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’ve about a week before my internship starts: I’m going to use that time to
build a nice front-end interface for my budgeting spreadsheet. The 2016 version
is honestly pretty shitty and messy and sometimes (I don’t know why) doesn’t work at all. I’m probably not going to build a full on app but perhaps just
a glorified form on mobile (maybe even using Google Forms but I kind of want to try out Vue), I think that would work great.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I also built a bash script (Mark’s idea) to make the process of 
updating this blog easier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#!/bin/bash&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#Generates the _site folder and moves its contents to the lieuzhenghong.github.io folder &lt;/span&gt;

bundle &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;exec &lt;/span&gt;jekyll build
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;DESTDIR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;../lieuzhenghong.github.io/
rm -rf ../lieuzhenghong.github.io/&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;
mv -v ./_site/&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$DESTDIR&lt;/span&gt; 
rm -rf ./_site/
rm -f &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$DESTDIR&lt;/span&gt;/build.she&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="monthly review" /><category term="progress report" /><summary type="html">these two chrysalid years are finally over: this is a period of unprecedented freedom and it’s imperative i don’t waste my time.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">October in review; plans for November</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/10/28/october-in-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="October in review; plans for November" /><published>2016-10-28T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-10-28T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2016/10/28/october-in-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2016/10/28/october-in-review.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/oct_16_calendar.png&quot; alt=&quot;october calendar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;October was the month of MOOCs. I read a grand total of zero books but I started
on CS50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;October was also the month of lapses: I started playing computer games again, spending ~10 hours on Dota 2, ~5 hours on Borderlands 2, and ~10 hours on CrusaderQuest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s &lt;strong&gt;three whole days of work&lt;/strong&gt; assuming 8-hour days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something I’m particularly ashamed of is the fact that I squandered the last week (24–28) after keeping up an admirable momentum for the first two–three weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I estimate that I’ve wasted around 8 days in total of a 28-day month and this is
of course unacceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to start planning my time better. In particular, after I ORD I will have
the freedom to structure my time to a far greater extent. No hour should be
wasted—this is the minimum modicum of discipline that I should expect from
myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other news, I realised that I’ve hit the 85kg 5x5 stated in my “current
projects” page. I also managed to bench 105kg ORM—I will update the current projects page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;projects-for-november&quot;&gt;Projects for November&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are my current projects for the month of November:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Smart home project
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The issue I’m currently facing now is a problem with serial output coming
 from Arduino. Instead of receiving data every line, sometimes I receive the
 data as follows: “line1 \n line2” as one data object.
 Mark suggested I write a buffer to print out the data line by line but…I’m
 not sure how to do it and have been putting it off.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Co{de}llective website
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This has to be up by 12th November: non-negotiable.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I’ve to get the site up and write some articles… shag af&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I realise that I’m less and less interested in webdev, at least building
 static websites… I learn nothing from it and it’s just really dull.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CS50: finish it up
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I started CS50 1st October and managed to do 5 problem sets in one month. I
 hope to be able to finish up CS50x by November and then start MIT’s
 Analytics Edge in December.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scholarships: look for and apply for them
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I have blocked off the months of Dec and Jan for travel. (December with
family; January with class) Hence, there won’t     be time for me to do
anything serious then.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;My scholarship deadlines are March—that means I have only one month + to
prepare and submit my scholarships.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;That’s why it’s important to start looking now (after November 12).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;currently-worrying-about&quot;&gt;Currently worrying about&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ORD
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I realise that I’m not looking forward to ORD as much as I should. I really
 wanted to ORD but now that it’s right around the horizon the sense of
 freedom has been relpaced with some sort of dread and I’m not (as) keen to
 ORD. The dread is the recognition that I will have an enormous block of free
 time and I will have the responsiblity of using it properly.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;There are also things that I previously took for granted in the army but
 can’t anymore: for example, I’ve to find a new gym and pay for it (TGN is 8
 dollars an entry; membership at 75 dollars a month)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scholarship
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Critical if I’m to go to Oxford—enough said&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Major choice
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Change major or no? Tech is becoming more and more relevant and I’m not sure
 about the relevance of a PPE degree.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="monthly review" /><category term="progress report" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An eventful Saturday</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/10/08/an-eventful-saturday.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An eventful Saturday" /><published>2016-10-08T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-10-08T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2016/10/08/an-eventful-saturday</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2016/10/08/an-eventful-saturday.html">&lt;p&gt;I woke up at 8:30 a.m. today and did a bit of Problem Set 4 in CS50.  Then I
went to teach the C4C P5 class (Dylan, Gao Hong, Audrey and Gillian).  Last
week, I taught them lessons 1 and 2 (the input and print command) and this week
I taught Python Turtle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have reproduced my message to the C4C P5 group here, as it nicely sums up how
the lesson went:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/audrey_gillian_yi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image posted by zhengyang&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;just to add a bit of context to Zheng Yang’s post, and a post-mortem of today’s
lesson:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have been teaching them Python for two weeks now according to my curriculum.
Last week they learned four main things:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;print()&lt;/code&gt; function,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;the concept of variables,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;taking user input with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;input()&lt;/code&gt; and&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;type conversion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We spent the first ~45 minutes of the day on recapping those four things.
Then we moved on to the next lesson, which is drawing with Python’s turtle
module.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The kids were all able to grasp the concept of the turtle very quickly— this
bolsters my confidence in Turtle as a teaching tool.  And the photo by Zheng
Yang is the Chinese character 易 done by Audrey and Gillian. I think it is
very nice.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Overall, all the lesson objectives were met and I was pleased with the
progress of the lesson. Audrey, Gillian and Dylan were focused and
well-behaved, Gao Hong not so much (but still relatively tractable). I would
like especially to commend Dylan, who went to the library to borrow a book
about Python programming on his own accord! Very pleased with his interest and
I feel that given his young age, he will be an accomplished coder very soon as
long as we continue to stoke his interest and challenge him. Maybe it’s not
too early to think about &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt; DSA…. 😂&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;One last thing —thanks to Zhen Yang and Poe for coming today. 
I hope to see all you guys again next week!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I met Mrs Hauw after the lesson. She had approached me earlier this week to
offer me an internship at Iglobe once I finish NS. She said on Telegram that the
internship would take about 6-8 months and I expressed this concern to her.
Whereupon she said “Since when I said 6-8 months? I told you Yau Xuan interned
for 6 months, you only need to do 4 months”…which was weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had some other concerns but she waved them aside… I told her that I had to
apply for scholarships whereupon she said “Aiya your scholarship need to apply
full time meh?” or something along those lines. She mentioned that she had
already received applications from undergraduates. I asked her how I would
represent skills that are non-credentialed (i.e. basically all programming
skills) and she said that it will show in the interview. I then asked “Then do I
have to do the interview?” and she smiled and said “I already interviewed you
already what.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She gave me some more tips about writing the CV and told me that “there’s no
such thing as modesty” when I said that I was reluctant to put non-credentialed
skills on my CV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I have read her correctly (and I could be wrong…) she is basically saying
that the CV is a mere formality and she already wants me for the job. 
But either way I
have to write a CV and make it a good one since this CV isn’t just for this
internship application, it’s for all subsequent applications so best to bite the
bullet and do it now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like I have a strong focus right now–tech, and teaching tech. I am
fortunate to have free rein over what I can teach the kids. That gives
me an advantage over others who may not be as focused in their CIP. But more on
strategic CV writing in a later post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After C4C and the meeting with Mrs Hauw I went to the gym with Chew (Delta Gym)
and both Chew and I failed all our lifts. It wasn’t even a good fail it was a
totally embarassing fail… like 2 reps and can’t push any more kind of fail.
Meh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-joosy-part&quot;&gt;The joosy part&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is when the really joosy part comes in. So after gym we called up Nauxiy
and asked him to join us for dinner. We agreed to meet at Star Vista.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Buona MRT, while we were taking the escalator down, Chew pointed out to me 
an old Indian man who looked like he was stuck on the escalator. From what we
could see, because he kept moving backward, it looked like his leg was stuck in
the escalator! I quickly ran down only to see the guy walking backwards,
barefoot, like it was the most normal thing in the world. He was facing the
“right” way (that is, the normal way) but walking backwards. I must confess that
I was completely taken aback as I had &lt;strong&gt;no fucking idea&lt;/strong&gt; what he was doing and
I just stood there not knowing what to do…
until some guy came behind me and pulled the man off the escalator. One
uncle asked him “Are you drunk?” and he mumbled, grinning, yes I am very drunk.
Thank you very much. 
The
uncle asked him to take the stairs and I watched him climb up the stairs
barefoot (his slippers were upstairs with another Indian man, his friend
probably).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until now I still don’t know what he was trying to do…lol&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had actually thought of pulling the Indian man off the escalator but I was
afraid that he would stumble and fall and really get something caught in the
escalator. I think this shows that my decision-making capability needs work
though I had no idea that he was drunk as I haven’t met many inebriated people
before. Maybe if I had known I would have acted faster. As it was I just stood
there like a fucking idiot lol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-even-joosier-part&quot;&gt;The even joosier part&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the even joosier part. We went to EighteenChefs (the Western food
place run by an ex-convict that specially hires ex-convicts to give them a
second chance). The food there was quite affordable. There was this NSF promotion
where baked cheese rice is only like 7.50 and it tasted pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was this large group of students (I think eight or ten people) who were
seated opposite us. I had my eye on a thick one (hehehe).
We were discussing whether they were poly or uni students but anyway they
finished and left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The waiter, this short guy with big round glasses and a full sleeve on his left 
arm, went
to separate the tables and clean up. I saw him take a phone from the chair and
grin as he walked away. I made a throwaway remark “lol the waiter just took
someone’s phone”. I didn’t think anything of it as I assumed that he was just
taking it for safekeeping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After like ten or fifteen minutes Thick and Thin came in looking very anxious.
They asked the waiter whether he had seen Thick’s phone and the waiter put on a
very concerned face and said no, whereupon he started putting up a big show
looking for the phone under the table and asking them to call the phone. His
&lt;em&gt;wayang&lt;/em&gt; was so good they should have given him golden horse! In fact it was so
good that I was gaslighted. Although I had definitely seen him take the phone I
became not so sure. But nonetheless I walked up to them after the waiter had
left to presumably look for the phone and asked them “You guys are looking for
your phone right?” and told them “I’m pretty sure I saw one of the staff take
your phone” whereupon they asked me, quite naturally, who was the staff member.
Again although I was quite sure it was that guy, I was i) gaslighted and ii) did
not want to accuse someone wrongly so I said that I wasn’t sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then because I was so gaslighted I actually went back to my table and asked the
gang whether I had actually seen the phone being taken? And &lt;em&gt;thank god&lt;/em&gt; I had
made that throwaway remark earlier because they confirmed that I had did indeed
said that and something as specific as “the waiter took a phone” is quite
reliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After five to ten minutes of what must be unadulterated panic felt by the girls,
they managed to get a hold of the manager who told them that he would go and
check the CCTV. After he went in he came out, returned the phone, and told them 
that the phone was
found &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; but to give them their phone number as he wanted to conduct an
“investigation”. I wasn’t smart enough to read the subtext but someone told me
that the manager said “outside” to safeguard the reputation of the restaurant
and in actual fact (of course) it was found in the grubby pockets of that fuckin
thief. Thus vindicated by this fact, I felt secure enough to tell Thick and Thin
that I was pretty sure that it was that waiter who took the phone. (And
apparently Nauxiy said that the waiter gave our table a really dirty look). The
girls thanked me and left. Nauxiy finished his waffle and we left.
江山易改，本性难移!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-could-i-have-done-better&quot;&gt;What could I have done better?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m in two minds about this incident. On the one hand, I think that I handled it
&lt;em&gt;okay&lt;/em&gt; compared to the drunken Indian man incident. But maybe I could have
handled it better? I played it too conservative and Bayesian and kept saying
that I wasn’t sure who the waiter was. But maybe I should have just walked up to
the waiter and told him something alpha like “brother, I saw you take the phone,
give it to us there’s no need to call police”. (And also I could have walked with 
them more all the way to help them solve the incident instead of returning to my table). 
After all, it was a public place,
I was bigger than him and wearing a singlet. But of course these are things that
are really &lt;em&gt;l’esprit de l’escalier&lt;/em&gt;… you fantasise about how you would have
done it in the &lt;strong&gt;cool&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;ALPHA&lt;/strong&gt; way but in the real world when it happens
you’re bo ji and do it the humji way, very 婉转!! And this 婉转 way definitely caused the girls some unnecessary anguish. So I have to train myself to be a more alpha
man and don’t be afraid of confrontation like a pussy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that is the takeaway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other thing (and this one I think it’s a real pity) is that I didn’t get
Thick’s number 😂😂. We were joking about it on the train like “since the
manager asked for her number you should’ve asked for her number too” but more 
and more I’m thinking that &lt;em&gt;maybe&lt;/em&gt; I should have done that… hahaha. After all
you did a good deed so that’s social proof that you’re a Good Person so why not
capitalise on the fact that you did her a huge favour and she has a good
impression of you to get to know her better right??? Of course (as nauxiy
rightly pointed out) that diminishes the goodness of the Good Deed but fuck it,
I don’t live to do good deeds but we literally live to get our dicks wet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also like neither of them thought Thick was chio so &lt;strong&gt;again&lt;/strong&gt; i was
mocked for my low standards and unorthodox taste. But there was a very cute girl
wearing a white dress and a choker (apparently that’s very hot to the two of
them) and we all agreed that she was chio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, that was my eventful Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><summary type="html">I woke up at 8:30 a.m. today and did a bit of Problem Set 4 in CS50. Then I went to teach the C4C P5 class (Dylan, Gao Hong, Audrey and Gillian). Last week, I taught them lessons 1 and 2 (the input and print command) and this week I taught Python Turtle.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building my first Telegram bot</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/09/20/building-my-first-telegram-bot.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building my first Telegram bot" /><published>2016-09-20T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-09-20T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2016/09/20/building-my-first-telegram-bot</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2016/09/20/building-my-first-telegram-bot.html">&lt;p&gt;I built my first Telegram bot, Charge Bot. The first commit was 3 days ago (18th
September) but I first started working on it on 27th August. Then I took a three-week
break and resumed working on it on 17th September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can check the bot out on Telegram &lt;a href=&quot;https://telegram.me/charge_game_bot&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;
The Github repo is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lieuzhenghong/charge-bot/&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This checked a couple of technical firsts for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First Telegram bot&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time I used Python to write anything substantial&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First deploy on Heroku&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time using non-ASCII characters and working with UTF-8 encoding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time using a linter (pylint)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also a couple of non-technical firsts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time building a multiplayer “game”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time building anything my friends can use&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time building something for public consumption (apart from a blog)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also the first time I wrote anything for public consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I am quite happy with this project. The scope was manageable and it did
not balloon (probably because it was a game and, being a game, the scope is rather
clearly defined; what also helped was the limitations of the Telegram medium). 
At the same time, I was able to incorporate user feedback and suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-it-works&quot;&gt;How it works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Python code to write a Telegram bot is extremely trivial.
It is just a while loop that sends HTTP requests with a long timeout (long
polling). Upon receiving a response, it sends the next request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is another way which is push instead of pull (doesn’t send requests: waits for
Telegram to send updates to you) but it is far more involved and wasn’t suitable for a
first-time project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here’s the code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;get_updates&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;URL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'getUpdates?offset={0}&amp;amp;timeout={1}'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;format&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;read_offset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3600&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;requests&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;handle_updates&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. But there was a gotcha: As my background is in Javascript where all responses
are asynchronous, the line &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;req = requests.get(string)&lt;/code&gt; tripped me up. If you were to write
that in Javascript you would get &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;req == undefined&lt;/code&gt; or something like that and thus
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;handle_updates(req)&lt;/code&gt; would throw an error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Python, the synchronous nature of the code means that the assignment operator will
actually stop the evaluation until it returns a proper result. That means no callback is
needed and the code becomes very simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;snafus&quot;&gt;Snafus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;modularisation&quot;&gt;Modularisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was something that I had a lot of trouble with, despite Mark’s best efforts to help me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My code is divvied up as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;* index.py (should be main.py): is the main file, imports everything
* network.py: sends requests and handles responses
* lobby.py: code that allows players to create and join a game
* game.py: game code
* charge_keyboard.py: the inline keyboard needed for the game
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was unable to understand the idea of a function that called another function (also known
as… a callback function LOL). Here’s what I had trouble with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# network.py&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setPushDataTo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;global&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;callback&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;callback&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;func&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;pushDataToDispatcher&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;global&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;callback&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;callback&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# index.py&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;network&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;init&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&quot;&quot;Initialises the app and sets up all callbacks&quot;&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;network&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;setPushDataTo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dispatcher&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;dispatcher&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, this pattern allows a function in one file to call a function in another file,
&lt;em&gt;without importing&lt;/em&gt;. The reason why we cannot import is because we don’t want a two-way
import (index imports network, not the other way round).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we still need some way for the “child” to communicate with the “parent” and the way
to do it is by setting the callback function in the “child” to the parent’s function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not sure I am explaining it clearly…I’ll come back in a few days to this post
and see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deploying-on-heroku&quot;&gt;Deploying on Heroku&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heroku was a real pain to set up…the documentation was lacking and I spent two nights’
worth just trying to figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gist of it is that you have to have a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;requirements.txt&lt;/code&gt; file, a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Procfile&lt;/code&gt; and a
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;runtime.txt&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “Getting Started with Heroku” tutorial mentioned the first two but not the last one!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;requirements.txt&lt;/code&gt; is just a list of dependencies… that’s quite straightforward
I still don’t know what &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;runtime.txt&lt;/code&gt; does but I had to put in the line &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python-3.5.2&lt;/code&gt; in
order for Heroku to deploy my app with Python 3. I needed Python 3 because of it’s native
Unicode handling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I mean by that is: when Python2 receives a response as a string, it doesn’t actually
use Unicode encoding. In order to get it as Unicode you have to put a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;u'&lt;/code&gt; in front of it.
Python 3 does this all by itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Procfile is also not straightforward. Basically the Procfile tells Heroku what kind of
dyno your app is (web, worker, something else), what file to run with what program. So
like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;worker: python index.py --loglevel=info&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Weirdly, typing python3 index.py throws some weird error and I don’t know why and haven’t
been able to Google)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bad-code&quot;&gt;Bad code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This app was developed very haphazardly, and it shows. I used tons of global variables
because I’m very bad. Coming from a Javascript background I don’t know how to use classes,
like, &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;. So it’s good that I’m learning Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried refactoring but it was truly a huge pain and I actually had to rollback to the
previous commit because I fucked everything up. 😭&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learning-points-and-future-plans&quot;&gt;Learning points and future plans&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to make as many bots as I can in the future, because Telegram is by far the most-used
app on my phone. It was extremely smart of the Telegram team to expose this API to developers–
this has allowed it to eclipse Whatsapp even further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my next app, I will definitely try and use the webhooks push method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heroku has a free dyno tier so I have &lt;strong&gt;no idea&lt;/strong&gt; why I’m paying 8 dollars a month to DigitalOcean.
I think that I will move my automated transaction tracker over to Heroku as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned the bad code: for my next app I am going to try and write it &lt;strong&gt;right&lt;/strong&gt; and I
know everyone says that but I mean it, I’m going to aim for 0 warnings on pylint!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, this was a good learning experience, I had fun. Am pretty psyched to build my
next Telegram bot!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><summary type="html">I built my first Telegram bot, Charge Bot. The first commit was 3 days ago (18th September) but I first started working on it on 27th August. Then I took a three-week break and resumed working on it on 17th September.</summary></entry></feed>