<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-09-18T23:20:29+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">lieu’s site</title><subtitle>my personal site</subtitle><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><entry><title type="html">2018 in review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/07/01/2018-in-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2018 in review" /><published>2018-07-01T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-07-01T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/07/01/2018-in-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/07/01/2018-in-review.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this is entitled “2018 in review”, it ends in June 2018. There are two
reasons for this. First, dividing up the year by the academic term is a much
more natural way to do it; I’ve just wrapped up my first year in Oxford and my
thoughts are much fresher than they would be if I waited until December to
write this post.  Besides, in December I’ll probably be writing my blog post
about Michaelmas 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I realised that I didn’t write a 2017 year-in-review post so I’ll use
this post to do that. Truth be told my memory of 2017 at this point is rather
hazy; I’ll have to look at my old posts to bootstrap my memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The older I get, the more grateful I am for having started this blog in 2016.
Otherwise I don’t remember the things I have done, but more importantly, I
forget many of the thoughts I had! The latter is critical to me because it’s
incredibly illuminating to look back on my past and see the anxieties I
suffered from. Do I still hold the fears I used to, or no longer, and why if
so—have I overcome them, or were they just idle worries? If the latter, can I
update my worry-heuristic so that I can better distinguish between “I need to
fix this NOW” and “this too shall pass”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;calendar-of-events&quot;&gt;Calendar of events&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Month&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;What I did&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Jan 17&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Went to Cebu, got a diving license, iGlobe internship&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Feb 17&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;iGlobe, started Andrew Ng’s ML course&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Mar 17&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;iGlobe – Form Letterer and Form Emailer&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Apr 17&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;iGlobe, applied for scholarships, finished ML&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;May 17&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;iGlobe, applied for scholarships, went to Japan, built Raspi console&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Jun 17&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Went to Yunnan, did 3D printing, went to NTU&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Jul 17&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Accepted the IMDA scholarship, won CodeXtreme 2017&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Aug 17&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Completed Inspector’s Gadget (Electron)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Sep 17&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Chiong MOOCs: Algos I, N2TI, How to Code&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Oct 17&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Enrolled in Oxford&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Nov 17&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;MT 2017: rowing, powerlifting, Micro, Logic&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Dec 17&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Finished N2T II, failed driving test&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Jan 18&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;HT 2018: powerlifting, Pracpol, GP/MP&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Feb 18&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;HT 2018&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Mar 18&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Ended HT 2018, telethon&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Apr 18&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;TT 2018: traveled Europe (Berlin, Warsaw, Holland)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;May 18&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;TT 2018: Theopol, Macro, revision&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Jun 18&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Prelims, ended TT 2018, IMDA internship&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;thoughts-about-this-year-and-a-half&quot;&gt;Thoughts about this year-and-a-half?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have had a great year and a half. Some of it is helped by the fact that
I have moved to a different stage of life, which has been incredibly exciting
and liberating. In &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/09/24/life-report-sep-2017.html&quot;&gt;September 2017&lt;/a&gt;
I wrote that “this post marks the end of an era… the chrysalid years are
over, and I fly to Heathrow to begin my new life as a student tomorrow night”.
And that’s exactly right. The start of 2017 marked my transition from soldier
to layabout, and 2018 the transition from layabout to student and young adult.
The challenges I face now are far more interesting and I feel like I have more
agency to tackle them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;academic&quot;&gt;Academic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to go to Oxford instead of NTU, and (while it’s difficult to know the
counterfactual) I think I made the right decision. I am flourishing. I’m
enjoying myself greatly. The rigour of writing essays twice a week clarifies my
thinking and stretches myself academically. Living out is a source of great joy
as I enjoy cooking for myself and my friends. I greatly cherish the privacy and
self-actualisation granted by my own independence. Being in a highly proximate
environment with like-minded friends means that I always feel enriched by their
close company and conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had doubts about PPE lacking rigour at the start but I now believe that if I
take the right quantitative modules and keep up my technology self-study, I
will be able to compete favourably with CS graduates. If nothing else, I have a
comparative advantage in the specific intersection of finance/econ and
coding—although I have heard that they still do prefer physics/maths/CS
grads. It will be up to me to pivot myself career-wise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as a degree I greatly enjoy the work I do in PPE—it is a truly
multidisciplinary degree, particularly in the first year.  I enjoyed writing
essays more than I expected.  There’s something about writing essays that
forces you to know your stuff and construct a clear argument in your head—You
don’t know you don’t know something until you’re forced to write an essay about
it. I’ve gotten better at this over time (as I should; setting aside Economics
essays, I wrote a total of 21 essays in 16 weeks and one more substantial
Q-STEP essay), and I look forward to increasing the speed with which I can
formulate a clear, succinct, and powerful argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still lack clarity. I can put forward most relatively straightforward
arguments with aplomb, but struggle with conveying certain more nuanced
arguments (that have multiple conditional premises/branching forks). For
example, A can either be B or C. If B, then D, which is not what we want, and
if C, then E, which contradicts A. Hence, ~A. I wrote two Theopol essays with
this structure (Rousseau and Marx) and they didn’t go well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have done relatively well this year, earning Fowler prizes every term. I was
well enough prepared for Prelims, particularly for Economics and Logic. I
didn’t do much revision for Theory of Politics but not much is needed to write
Theopol essays anyway. Unfortunately I made a wrong question selection for
Microeconomics my best paper and the Distinction is now in jeopardy.
Nonetheless, this is not a problem of insufficient preparation—it’s a problem
of bad exam strategy which I’ll have to remedy in the future. The key is
&lt;em&gt;reducing variance&lt;/em&gt;: choosing questions I am sure I can do reasonably well
rather than questions that I’m not sure I can do but could do very well on. I
made the same mistake on Logic with choosing the Natural Deduction question
(which was a huge departure from the norm), but luckily I managed to do it
well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-step-essay&quot;&gt;Q-Step essay&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am extremely pleased to have won the Q-STEP First Year Political Essay prize
for my essay &lt;em&gt;“Does Consensus Democracy Improve Economic Outcomes?&lt;/em&gt; which I
wrote during Hilary Term. This prize is awarded to the best essay (out of ~300)
which all HPol and PPE students had to write in our Quantitative Political
Analysis course, and it comes with 200 quid as well! It feels great to beat all
the other smart Oxford fuckers and come top of the year for &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;insert image here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t be too self-congratulatory, of course. It was more that I picked the
right battle. As this is a quantitative assignment, I knew that many PPE and
HPol students would not have the aptitude or interest to go above and beyond.
Further, I spent a lot of time during Hilary Term working on this essay, when
most people would have chosen to enjoy their term or revise for collections (in
truth, probably a better use of one’s time). It’s vanishingly unlikely that
I’ll be able to come top of the cohort in any other subsequent assignment or
paper, so I’ll take what I can get… haha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the essay &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/lieuzhenghong/qstep-essay&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. My
“excellent and novel contribution” was simply to extend Lijphart’s analysis in
two ways: i) using panel data and ii) bringing in more democracies. I showed
that doing so causes Lijphart’s purported relationship between consensus
democracy and social inequality (operationalised by the percentage of women in
parliament) to disappear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must thank Jarel for speaking with me about my essay and providing me with my
key theoretical insight, which came serendipitously two days before the essay
deadline! I had ran the regressions earlier and were very frustrated that I
couldn’t replicate Lijphart’s results. But Jarel said that in and of itself is
a very significant finding!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Jarel: let me get this right: when you control for fixed effects, effects on gender
become insignificant — right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Me: yes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Jarel: ok that’s a very strong result&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Jarel: i think i might have to rewrite the analysis bit as well&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Me: im very excited now actually because of what you pointed out&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Me: haha&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and there we go: the absence of result is indeed an interesting result. So I
quickly added this final keystone and submitted it the next day. I don’t think
my essay would have been nearly as strong without this spin on the essay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading the essay with a fresh eye (and with the help of the marker’s
comments), there are a couple of things I could have done better, which would
have pushed the essay from a 79 (High First; great work) to a 80 (Excellent
First; pretty much impossible to achieve). First of all, the
introduction/theoretical argument/methodological criticisms were written before
I had the key insight; I edited them hastily after-the-fact which necessarily
makes them a little disjointed and the key insight feel a bit tacked-on. I
should have put front-and-center the criticism that Lijphart selects on the
dependent variable by using FH to operationalise democracy. From the marker’s
report,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Argument: Your theoretical section mediates between Tsebelis and Lijphart,
whereas it would have been more convincing to derive unique theoretical
argument capturing your own intuitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There we go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must thank Sergi and Tak Huen for taking the time to look at my essay; in
particular my mentor Sergi, who was swamped running revision classes for the
PPE finalists. But most importantly Jeffrey, who was my QSTEP mentor and
actually Skyped me in Utah during the vac, and really went above and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I’ve learned:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pick your battles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sometimes serendipity plays a big part&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I worked extra hard and was rewarded for it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;extracurricular&quot;&gt;Extracurricular&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an area in which`I feel there is much room for improvement. By
“extracurricular” I refer to my CS self-study (MOOCs, algorithms practice) and
hobbies (cooking, lifting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cs-self-study&quot;&gt;CS self-study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was able to get some CS self-study done this Christmas (finished N2T II) but
no work done in Hilary as I was focused on my QSTEP, which had very rudimentary
R. I think I made the right choice focusing on QSTEP but I think that I could
have done more; one problem on Leetcode per day would have been a good start,
for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lifting&quot;&gt;Lifting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always suffered from a lack of motivation going to the gym: two steps
forward, one step back. This has caused my progress in the gym to be less than
it could have been, although I have made progress nonetheless. In the very
recent past due to my studying for Prelims (and spending time with my
girlfriend) I did not go to the gym regularly (at all) during Trinity term. But
I’m confident I will be able to make back my gains soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cooking&quot;&gt;Cooking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being in Oxford for a year and cooking for myself every day has thrown me in
the deep end. I’ve taken to this task with aplomb. In the first few months I
got used to stir-frying with a wok (the first time I did it I set off the smoke
alarm), and afterwards I branched out to oven baking/roasting and finally
cooking soup and cooking in the pressure cooker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cooking highlight of my year was cooking 500 portions of chicken
rice. It was Jing Long who recruited me for this event, an “Asian Food
Festival” hosted by Jovin. Jing Long bought an enormous rice cooker that
purported to be able to cook 200 portions of rice. We filled it up with water
and used it to sous vide ten whole chickens at a time, and it came out quite
like the real thing. Unfortunately the rice cooker let us down—the rice was
not evenly cooked, raw in parts and mushy in others—but the chicken was gucci
juicy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I plan to further improve my culinary skills with Jing Long this summer. We’re
going down to Jurong fish market this weekend at an ungodly hour—4am—to get
the freshest fish. We’re going to do sashimi and some other seafood, JL wants
to do chilli crab. I have a pressure cooker at home so I’m going to be
exploring all the recipes I can, particularly in making thick, rich soups and
broths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year JL and I want to do a “tasting menu” where we pull out all the stops
every month and cook fine dining for people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interpersonal&quot;&gt;Interpersonal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;relationship&quot;&gt;Relationship&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The largest interpersonal change in my life is that I am now in a relationship,
which has been very educational, quite challenging, and immensely rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/judy_and_me/1.png&quot; alt=&quot;at_formal&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/judy_and_me/2.png&quot; alt=&quot;punting&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/judy_and_me/3.png&quot; alt=&quot;in_sg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/judy_and_me/4.png&quot; alt=&quot;x&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A relationship takes up a lot of one’s time and I can better appreciate the
freedom one has as a single person. However I think our &lt;em&gt;raison d’etre&lt;/em&gt; is to
have the free time to spend it with our loved ones: family, friends, and
oneself. So it is a balance between loving oneself (striving for
self-improvement) and loving others (giving to our loved ones). A life only
loving oneself is a very lonely existence, so it’s important to give back to
others after an extended period of monk mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t mean to insinuate that getting into a relationship is purely selfless.
Obviously I derive pleasure and learning from a relationship. But
a relationship requires sacrifice that isn’t needed when one is single and
focused purely on improving oneself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I’ll very frankly list out some of the challenges that I’ve faced despite
the fact that my blog is now read by more than one person, as I have a strong
commitment to honesty (telling only the truth) and openness (telling the whole
truth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Low emotional sensitivity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My fatal flaw is I am not able to divine the feelings of others.  This has
often made me say the wrong thing in the past but I think I’ve gotten better at
this. Right now the problem is that I am not able to tell when my girlfriend is
angry or sad at something I’ve done or not done. When we first got together
I told her of this weakness and stressed the need for her to tell me exactly
how she feels. To her credit she has done so to a great extent, although not
for everything—but this is still incredibly admirable, because it’s very hard
to bare one’s feelings and I am sometimes guilty of not doing this myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She has done her part. On my part, it’s not fair to ask her to hold herself up
to a standard that even I can’t reach; I have to further improve my emotional
sensitivity despite my innate ineptitude, as well as to hold myself to the
standard I asked of my girlfriend to communicate honestly what I feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conflict management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve argued a couple of times. There are two aspects to this: first, how do
I not say or do things that will cause conflict; second, how do I best defuse
conflicts when they inevitably erupt?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pick one’s battles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no need to die on every hill; one can win battles and lose the war.
A relationship is predicated on give and take and if you want to win everything
you will lose your loved one. Nonetheless, there are of course important things
you want to change (the hills you’re willing to die on)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An uncertain future&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prospect of a long-distance relationship is an uncertain one. We will not
be studying in the same university next year, and we live in different
countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to serve a bond with IMDA, so my future for at least the next 7 years is
completely fixed. I told her that circumstances dictate I will have
to walk this path with or without her; I won’t be able to move to the US or the
UK, for example. I had to tell her because I don’t want to give anybody false
hope, or for her to have any possible misapprehension about what staying with
me entails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some closing thoughts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a wonderful thing to be able to love and to be loved; where it’s
acceptable to be needy/clingy/emotionally dependent on another person. The
conventional wisdom is that one should not be clingy but I find that if one is
so independent then what really is the point of a relationship?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;friends&quot;&gt;Friends&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have forged friends&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really, really like my tutors. Bassel, Sergi, Tia, Ralf—absolutely fantastic.
Their enthusiasm for the subject really shows through. In particular, the
politics tutors really sold me on the subject, when I wasn’t expecting to like
it at all. I was fully planning to drop politics… but now find myself wanting
to do a quantitative thesis!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tutorial on state paternalism was truly &lt;em&gt;life-changing&lt;/em&gt;. It completely
systematised and clarified my worldview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, I’m grateful to have come to Oxford: the tiny student-teacher ratio
means that I can forge close relationships with my tutors that wouldn’t be
possible at NTU. We go for drinks in the college bar, for example. I even
invited Bassel over and cooked Mapo tofu and egg fried rice for him!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;career&quot;&gt;Career&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I interned at iGlobe from January to May 2017. I did market research, due
diligence and wrote investment papers. I also wrote two programs, Form Letterer
and Form Emailer, using Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did well securing a scholarship. IMDA may not have the cachet of MAS/EDB/PSC,
but it’s a very good fit with my interests and I think I will enjoy the work
there more if I am given sufficient latitude. I’ve harped on this before but I
derive significant happiness from being financially independent, no longer
having to ask my parents for any money. It’s good too to be able to sock away
some money every month to buy slowly my freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am now working in Next-Generation Platforms, specialising in the blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I spent week 1 of 8 getting up to speed on the blockchain, and wrote a short
research paper on how to get different blockchains to interoperate with each
other.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am planning to spend the next few weeks developing the Hyperledger
blockchain for supply chain, first building the basic supply chain before
extending it to include features like tracking accidents, services, theft and
so on.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have been tasked to build a model that showcases the blockchain. This will
probably mean playing with model cars and trains and terrain, which promises
to be rather silly. Still, it’s a necessary step in order to get the layman to
understand what we are doing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;future-plans&quot;&gt;Future plans&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summer-2018-julyseptember&quot;&gt;Summer 2018 (July–September)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to do a good job in my internships at IMDA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want to implement a blockchain;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do something else that is quite technical in my next internship with
Planning, or at least useful for my future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to take, and finish, Algorithms II, and I plan to spend an hour a day on
it—no more, no less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I borrowed the book Functional Programming with Haskell by Richard Bird and
I intended to finish it but this is looking unlikely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will participate in a Codeforces educational challenge every week, as a way
to utilise my theoretical knowledge on Algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want to enjoy my summer with my family, partner and friends.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want to pursue cooking.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I want to get to a competitive powerlifting total:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Gymboxx 3 times a week&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Do some form of exercise every single day&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;michaelmas-2018-octoberdecember&quot;&gt;Michaelmas 2018 (October–December)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have more or less decided on the papers I’m going to offer for Finals. I’m
still waiting on the Department to approve my appeal to do a Politics thesis
without doing three other core Politics modules; Sergi and Tia are supportive,
and so are Rachel (Senior Tutor) and Katy (Academic Registrar). It will help if
I do well in my Prelims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Micro&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Macro&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quantatitive Economics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Microeconomic Analysis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Econometrics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Political Sociology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Theory of Politics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Thesis?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d love to take Game Theory and Behavioural Economics but I just don’t have
the space to fit them in. I wish I could drop Macro (Ian Crawford is in talks
with the PPE committee to do exactly this) but that won’t be available for our
year. If I could drop Micro I would take BE or GT right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am keeping Theory of Politics because I want to have a bit of Philosophy in
my degree (I am doing PPE, after all) and because I do quite enjoy the
topics, particularly on negative/positive liberty and paternalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Michaelmas term, there will be no excuse. I will be heading to Iffley thrice
a week and Merton gym thrice a week as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;medium-term-plans&quot;&gt;Medium-term plans&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next order of business is to &lt;strong&gt;secure an internship in my second year that
leads to a full-time job offer&lt;/strong&gt;. I would like to secure a “tech” job (meaning
a job where I write code for the majority of my day), but failing that, would
love to join IB or consulting with a focus in tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-i-have-changed-since-2017&quot;&gt;How I have changed since 2017&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to 2017, I feel more confident in my own abilities and my personality.
There is a lot I can work on but I know now that there are people who like me
for who I am, not &lt;em&gt;despite&lt;/em&gt; who I am. I am still very much rough around the
edges—I definitely could calibrate tact-being direct—but I am happy with
the general shape of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m happier than I was. Going to Oxford has given me a “low-grade” happiness
that’s not subject to hedonic adaptation. What that means is that occasionally
every couple weeks or so I’ll wake up, walk out of the door, and feel so
blessed to be here. This further cements my view that the things that truly
give me happiness isn’t things nor one-off experiences but
self-actualisation/self-improvement and having close relationships with my
loved ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples of things that don’t give me much happiness:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buying new clothes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buying new gadgets (SSD, phone, etc)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Traveling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last one took a bit of soul-searching. I enjoy some sorts of traveling but
not others. I enjoy traveling that’s chill and relaxed, and when I’m going to
see beautiful natural sights. I’m a bit of a homebody; I don’t feel the need to
make the most of my time when I’m in a foreign country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was difficult to realise this because traveling seems to be something that
everyone agrees is meaningful and worthwhile. But I feel like traveling is yet
another form of consumption, albeit a form that’s somewhat more socially
acceptable than purchasing material goods. I think it’s incorrect to draw an
artificial dichotomy between the two; material goods can bring one lasting
happiness (or at least freedom from a lasting annoyance), while the experience
from traveling can be very ephemeral. I think the sort of traveling where you
hop around countries and take photos of everything briefly is rather
meaningless, but I do enjoy spending a long time in a country and meeting new
friends or learning about new cultures. I did enjoy greatly my BSP experience,
as well as my trip to Yunnan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things that I have found do give me happiness:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having a sharp knife that makes kitchen prep easy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having a large pot and metal prep bowls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cooking (and eating) delicious meals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having a girlfriend&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Looking better&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being around friends all the time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buying things make me happier insofar as they reduce or remove a consistent
annoyance I suffer from. Everything else seems to be experiential or
self-actualising. I am happy when I am the best that I can be, and I am happy
when I am around the people I love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I feel more content and satisfied and happier than I was in 2017.
Thinking back to 2017, I was happy to have been done with NS, but not so happy
with the drudgery of my work and still worried about choosing between Oxford or
NTU. Now the grind and uncertainty still exists (I would never want it to go
away) but I feel far more secure in my life and future plans.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="annual review" /><category term="progress report" /><summary type="html">Introduction</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hilary 2018 report</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/03/10/2018-ht-report.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hilary 2018 report" /><published>2018-03-10T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-03-10T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/03/10/2018-ht-report</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/03/10/2018-ht-report.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-happened-this-term&quot;&gt;What happened this term&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first want to talk about the goals I set in December 2017 and which ones I’ve
achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;academic&quot;&gt;Academic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t hit my goal of two Firsts, although I was close. I did some good
revision for Economics and managed to get a score of 73, which would be higher
had I not made a silly careless mistake in the problem set. I’m very happy with
my essay (73 in both essay and problem set)—thanks to Harry, one of the
graduate mentors, for looking through my work and giving me good and actionable feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I didn’t do enough revision for Logic. I was able to smash the Natural
Deduction question (20/25) easily, but I didn’t do enough definition revision
(because it was hard). I have to stop being lazy and do important but difficult
revision rather than merely easy revision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expected that two essays a week would be tough, but I found it surprisingly
OK. I found myself enjoying politics more than I expected (Sergi is an absolute
dear), and am now flirting with the idea of doing politics instead of philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had our annual Warden’s collections. Every tutor said I was doing well.
Simon finally released his OXCORT which said that I am very fast and very
smart, although hampered by poor question selection, but he “[predicts] a clear
Distinction”. That’s good to hear. Sergi said I had three main strengths: I’m
quantitative and analytical, with an excellent grasp of research methodology.
I’m creative, with an interesting way of approaching the essays. Lastly, I’m
assertive: I write with a good tone (honed by many years of writing
argumentative essays, I suppose). However, I have two big flaws. Firstly, I
generally have trouble tying the readings with the essay question. This doesn’t
make my essays bad; they are still “decent to good”, but I will need to read
more comprehensively and holistically throughout the vac to round out my
undertanding. Secondly, I am too ambitious: I try to cover a lot of ground in
my essays but sacrifice depth as a result. He said that I often hit upon a very
good point but then just touch and go, whereas if I’d really focused on it it
would be extremely strong. So these are my two main problems. Bassel had only
nice things to say, he liked my collections and my learning attitude, but I
shan’t go into too much detail as I don’t want this paragraph to be too
self-congratulatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I had a good term academically, I think I put good effort into my
essays (most weeks), and had less motivation/momentum issues this term than in
Michaelmas term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;physical&quot;&gt;Physical&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was quite consistent these past eight weeks and have made reasonably good
progress. However, I often skip the light session on Wednesday and I always
skip deadlifts, which is bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My last workout on Friday 9th March was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Squat 130kg 3x5;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bench 88kg 5x5;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deadlift DNL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am happy with the progress I have made on both the squat and the bench. I
feel like I have a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of room left to grow on the squat, as the sets are
reasonably easy— which is good, because the people doing Varsity this year in
my weight class were squatting 180, 190 and pulling 200kg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t row at all this Hilary, which was probably a good idea because it was
extremely cold and a couple of days in Torpids were cancelled because of the
snow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;career&quot;&gt;Career&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not so good; one of the internships was called off. My handler left IMDA so I
have a new handler. But I really really need to clear both internship
obligations in one summer. I will follow up with my new handler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I received my allowance from IMDA in January but haven’t put it in the S&amp;amp;P500
yet. This is unacceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to borrow Conor’s computer and do the stupid stock quiz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;social&quot;&gt;Social&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like I have made some progress on my relationships. I have cooked for
several people that I didn’t in Michaelmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the fact that the cliques in Merton have solidified a little bit, I was
still able to make some new friends. I think if I want to make new friends, I
should head over to the bar more.  I feel like I have gotten closer to some
people that I already knew in Michaelmas, like Leo, Filip and Julianna (you’ll
have to ask them whether they feel the same way).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am still single but it doesn’t bother me that much right now. I still have to
figure out i) exactly what I want in a relationship and ii) whether or not
anyone will agree to exactly what I want, and if not do I change what I want or
do I stay single? At the current moment, I am not interested in getting with
random girls from Bridge either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-comments&quot;&gt;Other comments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;areas-for-improvement&quot;&gt;Areas for improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like in Michaelmas, cooking takes up too much time. However, I really
enjoy it. Furthermore, cooking for myself means I’m able to know exactly how
much protein I eat. I think I want to cook for only one other person every
day—I’ve found how easy and quick it is to cook for one after cooking for
myself during Telethon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to fix my sleep schedule as I was sleeping at 2am and waking up at 11am
or noon and missing lectures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gym-wise, don’t skip the Tues Thurs Wed Sat workouts, and don’t skip deadlifts
either!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social wise, maybe I will want to ask people to come and join me for dinner one
on one? Would that be too weird?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plans-for-the-vac&quot;&gt;Plans for the vac&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m spending Week 9 and 10 doing the Telethon. The shifts on weekdays start
from dinner in the hall at 1745 and end at 2130, which means I have the
daylight hours to go to the gym and study hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 hours in gym, 1 hour meal, 1 1/2 hour degree, 1 1/2 hour computer science
makes a total of 6 hours a day. Meaning I have to start my day at 1100 which
isn’t too bad lol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When am I going to start my QSTEP planning? I think devote half an hour per day
thinking, drafting out topics, exploring Lijphart’s data a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things I have to do for my degree:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research and write a honourable-mention QSTEP essay.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Practice essays for Politics and Philosophy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go back and revise Logic again, working through the ND pack paying attention
to the questions I missed the last time, and really nailing down the
definitions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things I have to do for CS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Linear Algebra (finish ASAP! I actually still have so many worksheets left; 5 6 7 1 2 3 4)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leetcode (If I do a problem a weekday, I can make really good progress.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to read for Politics, and do practice essays for Politics and
Philosophy, to get the feel of writing essays under time pressure. I’ll contact
the Graduate Mentors (Luke, Harry) and ask them for help over the vac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, I’m going to travel Europe. I may or may not do work during that time; we’ll see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goals-for-next-term&quot;&gt;Goals for next term&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;academic-1&quot;&gt;Academic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m OK with a &amp;gt;65 for Politics and Philosophy collections, no First needed.
Would be nice to have one First though, just to keep the 40 pounds rolling in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Distinction (200/300) for Prelims is &lt;em&gt;non-negotiable&lt;/em&gt;. I’m not aiming to get
any higher than that because it doesn’t really matter, though I think Jarel got
216 or something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I definitely want to get a First in Economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work out 6 days a week consistently.
Not to wake up after 9am on weekdays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Squat 145 x 5&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bench 95 x 5&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deadlift 150 x 5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;physical-1&quot;&gt;Physical&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, to be competitive for Varsity I at least need a 450kg total.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably want to bulk a bit until 72 then slowly cut down to look good for
summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I can squat 150kg for 6 reps or 155kg for 5 reps, that’s equivalent to 180kg
ORM (according to the calculator). I think a good goal is 145kg x 5 by summer,
and 155 x 5 by Varsity, to hit a 180kg squat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the calculator is underestimating how much I can bench, because I’m
quite sure I can do 100kg for a double. It would be amazing to hit 95kg x 5 by
summer and 102.5kg x 5 for Varsity for a very respectable 120kg ORM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not skip deadlifts and look into learning sumo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;social-1&quot;&gt;Social&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I want to get attached, I must be very clear with what sort of relationships
I am looking for at this moment. Then I can think about who do I like, why do I
like them, how do I go for them and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then the summer break is very long. Maybe better to do it 2nd year
Michaelmas. Otherwise if I get together with someone in Trinity also very hard
to 熬… See how la. Not like I anytime want to get can get…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;extracurricular&quot;&gt;Extracurricular&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judy mentioned that we can plan an OXCAR trip to Netherlands in Trinity. Just
two days maybe, because I’ve to study for my Prelims. If I am judicious and
hardworking in the vac, I’ll be able to go.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="progress report" /><summary type="html">What happened this term</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Michaelmas 2017 report</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/12/05/life-report-dec-2017.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Michaelmas 2017 report" /><published>2017-12-05T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-12-05T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/12/05/life-report-dec-2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/12/05/life-report-dec-2017.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;general-comments&quot;&gt;General comments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much has happened in so little time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Term is short but feels like forever—can’t wait to go back home, take a break,
then grind again&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People in Oxford are &lt;em&gt;smart&lt;/em&gt;… not patting myself on the back here but they
really just think fast, move fast, everything also fast. I am now definitely
not the smartest guy in the room anymore; not even close!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was able to get settled in alright quite quickly. Oxford is really intense.
Even though my workload is not heavy, there are just so many things happening
every single day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful to have had this slow term to kind of warm up to the work at
Oxford. I’ve been able to try a lot of things and do a lot of things (in effect
biting more than I can chew) that I wouldn’t have time for were it not for this
slow start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will talk about the different facets of my time at Oxford (academic,
interpersonal, extracurricular) and how I can improve these facets next turn.
Lastly, I’ll lay out my plans this holiday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;academic&quot;&gt;Academic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Couldn’t change course to Computer Science. But all is well—I am happy to do
PPE and learn computer science over the holidays. Bassel told me about the
Imperial CS course for non-CS undergraduates and I could do that one as well
apart from the Georgia Tech program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing alright. But not top of the pack by any means: Filip, Dylan, Conor all
really smart and Ton is another level altogether&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every week kind of fall back a bit a bit so I really welcome this chance to
catch up and consolidate&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motivation is finite and I lost momentum in the last two weeks, churning out an
essay I wasn’t proud of. This is unacceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have to work smarter, more efficiently. Learn to take notes. Retention was very
poor this term, so have to learn to take notes and absorb the material more
efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not been able to do &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; CS self-study. I was supposed to do Prog 1a,
Prog 1b, uMSC II and N2T II and I did none of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the problem is that I’ve been stuck on project 10 of N2TII for the
longest time. It’s a very difficult assignment and I want to move on but I
can’t bring myself to give up on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no way I’ll be able to do any CS self study next term, I suspect. I
reckon the most I can give is 1 hour per day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This holiday I will definitely die die finish up N2T II.
I also want to do the LinAlg course and also do problems on LeetCode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;next-term&quot;&gt;Next term&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cannot avoid inevitable memory work (in definitions for both economics and
logic). Practice some more formal logic and deduction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really look forward to writing philosophy essays! Politics not so much, but
QSTEP could be interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Definitely no time to work on CS come next term; it’s going to be crazy. Two
essays a week and so much readings to do as well. Don’t forget QSTEP…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next term I’ll have to go for lectures and actually take down notes. The notes
I took in MT 2017 will have to be gone through again, I’ll have to think about
the formatting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Study skills, study habits: working in OWL is unproductive, working at my
laptop is distracting because I have the bad habit of constantly switching to
and from tabs once the going gets even a little bit hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8 weeks, 16 essays, QSTEP. Politics tutes on Tuesdays/Wednesdays. Will need to
have a routine of work: when to do the readings, when to start writing the
first draft of the essay, etc&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, consistency is key&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;extra-curricular&quot;&gt;Extra-curricular&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This term, I did rowing, powerlifting, OXCAR. Cooking is also kind of an
extracurricular I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cooking&quot;&gt;Cooking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cooking takes too long a time: about 2 hours per session. Ways to optimise, in
decreasing order of preference/effectiveness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook for fewer people/ cook for multiple days at a time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buy groceries in batches, don’t buy every day&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook simpler dishes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eat early supper instead&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Skip dinner and have snacks instead (toast with cheese and ham etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cooking for myself is the only way to do a low-carb, high protein diet though.
If I’m convinced of the merits of such a diet, I will have to cook for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rowing&quot;&gt;Rowing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a fan of waking up at half 5 and walking 20 minutes in the cold dark to the
boathouse. &lt;em&gt;Especially&lt;/em&gt; not a fan of the 30-minute bike ride to Godstow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tom Murphy psychoed me to buy the AIO though, so the option to row is still
open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;powerlifting&quot;&gt;Powerlifting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like powerlifting because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have a decent build for it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I already have a good base (275 Wilks at the novice powerlifting meet)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the total I have to hit to be competitive doesn’t seem very far away&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it’s a very low-variance sport compared to other sports that are eligible
  for Blues.
That’s why I want to take it seriously if my injury will allow.
That means making it into Varsity next year (Hilary 2019) and getting a
Full Blue by the time I graduate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need a Wilks score of 350 for a Half Blue and 375 for Full Blue:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;~450kg (1000lb) for 350 Wilks, and 500kg for 375 Wilks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still thinking of what the best time to go to the gym is. The most
important thing is being consistent and going Mon, Wed, Fri &lt;em&gt;every single week&lt;/em&gt;
for 8 weeks. It shouldn’t be that hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;well, quite hard considering OXCAR had an Xmas concert on Wednesday&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was thinking of blocking out 5–7 but that would make me miss early supper. If
I went later then it’d be a bit crowded. Any earlier and I’d be too full from
lunch… problematic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;oxcar&quot;&gt;OXCAR&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I joined OXCAR, the Oxford Chinese Acapella Repetoire. Bryce and Eliza are in
it as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although training is by right only once a term, by left we have had tons of
extra rehearsals so the commitment level was more than advertised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t mind, though. I think I will do this for all three years at Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;next-term-1&quot;&gt;Next term&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drop rowing or only go once a week&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implement one or some of the possible solutions to cooking taking too long.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on powerlifting: I want to hit a 300 Wilks score by putting up a 385kg
total at this year’s Varsity tryouts. Last total at meet: 347.5kg (we’ll call
it 350kg) at 65.1kg. That was a 275 Wilks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interpersonal-relationships&quot;&gt;Interpersonal relationships&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Close friends made in PPE and North Lodge (Oskar, Rayhan); other friends seem
to be quite hi-bye&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can I have a deeper and more personal connection with the friends I make in
university? This is an open question I don’t have the answer to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;are-there-any-differences-between-singaporeans-and-angmohs&quot;&gt;Are there any differences between Singaporeans and angmohs?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are people—it’s hard to tell. I personally haven’t noticed much of a
difference but then again I’m not a very socially attuned person either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;next-term-2&quot;&gt;Next term&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not sure what I can do on this front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;people-i-am-especially-grateful-to&quot;&gt;People I am (especially) grateful to&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bassel, for being so patient and accommodating when I wanted to switch to
Compsci and for being an excellent tutor overall&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Oskar, for kindly hosting me in his room, sharing his food with me, buying
 groceries with and for me, and for having such a big heart&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leo, my tute buddy dinner kaki, and the person I hang out with most&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Martin, who has never once missed a dinner I’ve cooked&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tak Huen and Venla, for being great college parents: they patiently answered so
many of my questions before I came here&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dylan and Connor, who had all the answers when the rest of us were blur
cocks, and for being real good sports and a real hoot to hang with&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Xue Heng, who took out so much of his time to make me not so shit at
singing, and single-handedly saved my performance at OXCAR’s Xmas concert.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-am-i-doing-this-holiday&quot;&gt;What am I doing this holiday?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Career goals
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Send IMDA my academic plan and CV, start applying for internship w them&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Also, apply for internship with a firm in either SG or UK this summer.
 Otherwise I won’t have anything to do this summer after my IMDA internship.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I’m not interested in consulting; more interested in writing code&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consolidate my knowledge for Economics and Philosophy
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I think I’m 60% on both subjects, definitely quite shaky&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Write good notes for Economics; definitions, problems, diagrams&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do vacation reading to prepare for Hilary term:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mill, &lt;em&gt;Utilitarianism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Russell, &lt;em&gt;Problems with Philosophy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lijphart, &lt;em&gt;Patterns of Democracy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;some other readings specified in the Politics handout&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continue working on CS curriculum
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Solve Leetcode problems, embark on LinAlg course (with the help of Oskar’s
 lecture notes)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Learn C++/ C&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gym
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Consistency is key. Will make gains iff I go consistently.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Driving
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try and pass lor.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="progress report" /><summary type="html">General comments</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sep 2017 report</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/09/24/life-report-sep-2017.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sep 2017 report" /><published>2017-09-24T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-09-24T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/09/24/life-report-sep-2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/09/24/life-report-sep-2017.html">&lt;p&gt;This post marks the end of an era. The chrysalid years are over, and I fly to
Heathrow to begin my new life as a student tomorrow night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am wary, yet cautiously optimistic about the new academic demands Oxford will
soon impose on me. I have always been able to coast on by in my education,
accepting mediocre grades in return for not studying at all (being a supremely
lazy person). I won’t accept mediocrity any more and I look forward to studying
as hard as I can and getting the best grades my brain (and Fate) will allow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since my &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/08/22/life-report-aug-2017.html&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; I have done the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Embarked on my CS study plan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Went to OUMSSA orientation camp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cs-self-study-plan-and-milestone-goals&quot;&gt;CS self-study plan and milestone goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my previous post I mentioned that I have a “new and very ambitious goal”: to
be accepted into Georgia Tech’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.omscs.gatech.edu/&quot;&gt;Online Master of Science Computer Science
(OMSCS)&lt;/a&gt; in three years’ time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a good goal but I realise that it’s useful to signpost the endgoal with
various milestones along the way. To be accepted by OMSCS is after
all a very lagging indicator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I &lt;strong&gt;aim to do at least one technology internship over the
next two summers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A “technology internship” is defined as an internship in which I am expected
to program as part of my job scope. It would of course be best to intern at a
Big 5 company. Failing that, I wouldn’t mind interning either at a bank
(perhaps doing some financial analysis–make use of my PPE knowledge), a
“normal” tech company, a startup, GovTech, or working under a professor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will have to start looking for internships at the end of Michaelmas term this
December. To that end, I think I will have to bring forward my data science and
data analytics learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of programs out there:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Udacity’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://
           www.udacity.com/course/data-analyst-nanodegree--nd002&quot;&gt;Data Analyst Nanodegree&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DataCamp’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datacamp.com/tracks/data-scientist-with-python&quot;&gt;Data Scientist with Python&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datacamp.com/tracks/data-scientist-with-r&quot;&gt;Data Scientist with
  R&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datacamp.com/tracks/quantitative-analyst-with-r&quot;&gt;Quantitative
  Analyst with R&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Udacity nanodegree is $699 USD and Datacamp’s programs work on a
subscription basis: $25 USD/month. Not sure which one to go for… need to do
more research. At the moment, though, I have my hands full with the Nanodegree
as well as the programming languages course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September, I started my CS study plan and finished the following courses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NAND2Tetris, Part I (IIT)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Algorithms: Design and Analysis, taught by Tim Roughgarden (Stanford)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to Code: Simple Data (UBC)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m currently working through:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NAND2Tetris Part II&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I aim to finish it before matriculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a real slog to finish these courses, as I compressed a 6-week course
into 1 week (N2T I) and I didn’t give myself any breaks. Unfortunately I don’t
think this blazing fast pace is sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finishing these three courses, I realise that my old academic plan is not
ideal. In my rush to “finish” all the courses I don’t think I have allocated
enough time to synthesising the knowledge gained in the courses, which is what
truly matters. I think that if I don’t do any project that uses the knowledge
I learn in the course, I will forget what I have learned extremely quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I feel that my academic plan should include a “review week” or
“synthesis week” where I build a project that makes use of everything I learn
in the courses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should also make sure to add “breather weeks” after an intense period of
studying. I think a good breakdown is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;8-week timetable (term time)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;6 study weeks&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 recess week&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 project  week&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6-week timetable (holiday)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4 study weeks&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 recess week&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 project week&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, apart from doing projects, I should also dedicate my time to solving 
algorithmic problems in order to “crack the coding interview”. It would be good
if I could dedicate some time to practice questions on Leetcode. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.teachyourselfcs.com&quot;&gt;Teach
  Yourself CS&lt;/a&gt; recommends 100 problems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For practice, our preferred approach is for students to solve problems on
Leetcode. These tend to be interesting problems with decent accompanying
solutions and discussions. They also help you test progress against questions
that are commonly used in technical interviews at the more competitive
software companies. We suggest solving around 100 random leetcode problems as
part of your studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I want to be prepared for the internship then I will have to solve at least
50 problems by the end of Trinity Term. That’s ~1.5 problems per week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;algorithms-design-and-analysis-algos-i&quot;&gt;Algorithms: Design and Analysis (Algos I)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very rigorous course. The lecturer took me through the “greatest hits” of
computer science. In six weeks I learned the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Big O notation and how to calculate the running time of recursive algorithms
using the Master Method&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strassen’s matrix multiplication algorithm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quicksort, Mergesort, and analysing the running time of randomised algorithms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Graph search (DFS, BFS); computing strongly-connected components&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greedy algorithms: Dijkstra’s algorithm for graph search&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data structures: heaps, binary trees, hash tables, bloom filters. I learned
what each data structure is, what operations they support (and their running
times), and their limitations and applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were 6 programming assignments. I was only able to finish 4 of them; I
could not get the right answer for Quicksort (although my sorting algorithm
works fine) and I couldn’t calculate strongly-connected components at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish that I had more support in my computer science journey. When I get stuck
it’s hard to find help. That’s the good thing about studying computer science
in NUS (or any university for that matter): you can get help very easily. I
have to go at it alone, and this comes with its own difficulty. If everything
goes smoothly one can be even more productive than studying in university
because you can go at your own blistering pace and you don’t have to follow the
pace of the curriculum. But once you get stuck, it’s very hard to progress on
your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an example of what I mean. I spent almost a week trying to debug my
implementation of Dijkstra’s algorithm.  I stared at the algorithm very
closely, implemented and reimplemented it in a clean-room environment…
nothing worked. The problem was it couldn’t reach vertices it was supposed to
be able to reach. I kept poring over the algorithm again and again and looked
at how I was reading the text file… nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After consulting with many friends (many couldn’t help me because they were
busy or unwilling to debug for me—can’t say I blame them!) someone finally
found the problem. It turns out that the problem was caused by the adjacency
list representation I was given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the adjacency list representation for an undirected graph:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;1 [2,4], [3,8]
2 [3,6]
3 [4,2]
4 [1,7]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This adjacency list representation means that there is an edge between 1 and 2
with distance 4, and an edge between 1 and 3 with distance 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What my implementation did was faithfully transcribe this representation which
would be incorrect. It built an edge &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1 -&amp;gt; 2&lt;/code&gt; with distance 4 but not the
corresponding edge &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2 -&amp;gt; 1&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The correct representation of the graph should be as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;1 [2,4], [3,8], [4,7]
2 [3,6], [1,4]
3 [1,8], [2,6], [4,2]
4 [1,7], [3,2]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would never have found this bug in a million years as I had tunnel vision-ed
on the algorithm and the input processing. It never once occurred to me to
check the input itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-code-simple-data-μmsc-i&quot;&gt;How to Code: Simple Data (μMSc I)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A gentle introduction to programming best practices based off
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/&quot;&gt;SICP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a 6-course Software Development MicroMasters offered by edX.
The whole thing costs 832.50 USD and I’m not sure whether or not to pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course uses a language called Beginning Student Language (BSL), a subset of
Racket. The cool thing about DrRacket the IDE is that it allows you to paste
images right within the IDE and use it as a variable. So you can create
graphical/interactive programs very easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course taught a way to design functions and programs. Something I found
really interesting was the way we were taught to write functions that operate
on lists. Instead of writing a for loop over a list, we were forced to write a
recursive function instead acting on the head of the list and the rest of the
list. Here’s what that looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-racket highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;sum_all&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;loi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;cond&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;empty?&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;loi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;first&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;loi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;sum_all&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;rest&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;loi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)))]&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;instead of, for example,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;sum_all&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;loi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;loi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course also teaches you to write unit tests for every function you write:
the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;check-expect&lt;/code&gt; function of Racket made testing very low-friction. I
realised that writing tests really &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; all it’s cracked up to be, provided you
write the correct test cases: it gives you the assurance that the part of the
code is correct and this helps debugging immensely because you won’t waste your
time looking at already-correct code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like the course so far although it’s not as “hard” as Algorithms I. I
will definitely continue with the MicroMasters Series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nand2tetris-i-and-ii-n2ti-n2tii&quot;&gt;NAND2Tetris I and II (N2TI, N2TII)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A project-based course that has you write an operating system starting from
NAND gates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is absolutely my favourite course. I really like how this course gives me
a big-picture, 30000-feet view of computer architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first part of the course you build a computer first by building
electrical gates using a hardware description language. After you build basic
gates like XOR, AND, and MUX (multiplexer), you progress to build not-so-basic
gates like adders, finally progressing to the ALU, RAM, and the CPU. You also
learn to write in machine code and build an assembler for that machine code. I
had a ton of fun building the assembler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second part of the course has you writing the majority of the software for
the course. As the compilation is two-tier (high-level language -&amp;gt; VM -&amp;gt;
assembly code) you first write a VM -&amp;gt; assembly translator. Then you write a
program in Jack, the Java-esque high-level language of the course. For my
project I wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lieuzhenghong/nand2tetris-dropship-chess&quot;&gt;“dropship chess”
simulator&lt;/a&gt; and
plan to return to it soon (to fix bugs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/chess/dropship-chess.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;dropship-chess-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After writing a Jack program you then write the compiler for Jack (where I am
now). Finally, you write the OS for the computer and you’ll have built
a computer that can play Tetris (in my case, chess) from scratch!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think what makes this course so surprisingly manageable is the very
successful way in which the course designers manage complexity. At every step
the complexity of the system increases but it never becomes unmanageable,
because learners can simply abstract away the implementation they did in the
previous module/level of abstraction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-preliminary-thoughts-on-my-future&quot;&gt;Some preliminary thoughts on my future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am extremely fortunate to have a scholarship. At the age of 21 I am now
completely financially independent, and how many can say that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am really looking forward to managing my money in Oxford: budgeting
for rent and food, saving up for the big things I want to buy and do, investing
  to secure my future financial independence…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I plan to save 200 pounds per month for “delayed gratification” stuff and
invest 300 pounds a month. I will try to live on 800 pounds per month, 300 of
which will go to rent. We’ll see if I can live on 500 pounds per month (I
probably can if I cook sometimes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m worried about balancing work with my extracurriculars. There are a lot of
clubs I want to join and I may consider doing a sport or choir or whatnot but
can I do that while studying hard for PPE and CS?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="progress report" /><summary type="html">This post marks the end of an era. The chrysalid years are over, and I fly to Heathrow to begin my new life as a student tomorrow night.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Aug 2017 report</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/08/22/life-report-aug-2017.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aug 2017 report" /><published>2017-08-22T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-08-22T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/08/22/life-report-aug-2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/08/22/life-report-aug-2017.html">&lt;p&gt;Since my 
&lt;a href=&quot;/2017/05/29/monthly-report-may-2017.html&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; I have done the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Went to Yunnan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dabbled in 3D printing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepared the kids for CodeXtreme 2017&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turned 21&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matriculated at NTU&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Participated in two NTU orientation camps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Withdrew from NTU&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Got IMDA’s NIS scholarship&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Built my first piece of native production software using Electron&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;went-to-yunnan&quot;&gt;Went to Yunnan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went with Samuel and Jian Kai and I had a great time. We did a lot of walking
and hiking and the 12-day trip came to about $1,200.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were very nice to me even though I don’t really know them. Mad props to
them for even letting me go on the trip with them in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved the snow-capped mountain and the hike through Tiger Leaping Gorge: took
a lot of pictures with Jian Kai’s DSLR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yulong-snow-mountain&quot;&gt;Yulong Snow Mountain&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/me.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/snow-mountain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/landscape.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tiger-leaping-gorge&quot;&gt;Tiger Leaping Gorge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/landscape-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/gorge.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/landscape-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/group-photo-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-places&quot;&gt;Other places&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/landscape-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/me-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/group-photo-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Jeff, our Dali host, I was able to watch a master calligrapher at
work, who specialises in reversed writing.
He has been practicing this for over forty years now and his writing is
critically acclaimed. We were able to get four pieces from him for free (he
usually charges); I am extremely grateful for his generosity, and to Jeff as
well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/master-at-work.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yunnan/callig.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, a great trip—thanks to Sam and JK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dabbled-in-3d-printing&quot;&gt;Dabbled in 3D printing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built a burr puzzle as a gift to Wei Heng to thank him for lending me his SUICA
card and travel adapter for my Japan trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/3d-printing/burr-puzzle-split.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;burr puzzle pieces&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/3d-printing/burr-puzzle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;burr puzzle pieces assembled&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cube in cube was just for fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/3d-printing/cube-in-cube-raw.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cube-in-cube-raw&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/3d-printing/cube-in-cube-.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cube-in-cube-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/3d-printing/cube-in-cube-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cube-in-cube-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prepared-the-kids-for-codextreme-2017&quot;&gt;Prepared the kids for CodeXtreme 2017&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The annual hackathon event. I took Audrey, Gillian and Gao Hong; Dylan was
taken by Eng Chye. Got to know Van, a final year student at NUS SoC. She helped
me greatly in the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We built a micro:bit “magic wallet” implementation, and also a little LEGO
umbrella dispenser. We demonstrated the ability to use the micro:bit to send
and receive user-specified amounts of money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/microbit-wallet/group-photo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;''&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/microbit-wallet/group-photo2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;''&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Looking glam in slippers&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/microbit-wallet/dylan-team.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;''&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/microbit-wallet/microbit-wallet-poster.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;microbit-wallet-poster&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My team took third place, and Eng Chye’s team took first. Mrs Hauw was thrilled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;turned-21&quot;&gt;Turned 21&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I treated the gang to a buffet to celebrate. The food was pretty good but Nauxiy
was so shag after his hall camp he could barely keep his eyes open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is normally where I would write about trying to be more mature and
quitting gaming and all sorts of things but this post is very very long and
besides, every year I say the same things…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/2017-birthday/2017-birthday.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;''&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marc and I will be leaving for the UK and the rest will be staying in
Singapore. I hope the six of us last long and all of us find happiness and
success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;matriculated-at-ntu&quot;&gt;Matriculated at NTU&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing to say here&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;participated-in-two-ntu-orientation-camps&quot;&gt;Participated in two NTU orientation camps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Met new people&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like the people in NTU; they are really genuine and down-to-earth. I
participated in Banyan hall camp and SCSE’s faculty orientation camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/ntu/ravenclaw.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;''&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really will miss my OG mates and I do sincerely hope that they’ll want to
keep in touch even after I go overseas to study….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;withdrew-from-ntu&quot;&gt;Withdrew from NTU&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had to be done; I had fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I plan to visit for one final week (25,26,27,28,29) and stop going after 1st
September to focus on my MOOCs and prepare for Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;got-imdas-nis-scholarship&quot;&gt;Got IMDA’s NIS scholarship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will reproduce what I wrote in May here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was rejected from both GIC and MAS in the penultimate round, the ‘group
  discussion’ round… perhaps my personality was too abrasive. Unfortunately the
  scholarship agencies don’t give feedback on unsuccessful applications.
  Nevertheless, it was a good learning experience; I don’t regret the application
  process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The last scholarship I am waiting for is IMDA. As of this moment, IMDA is
  trying to schedule an interview slot with the directors. I told them that I
  would be willing to cancel my trip to Yunnan if need be; nothing to do now but
  wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off:
Although MAS does not give feedback, I was extremely fortunate to have had Ms
Nair who did:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/scholarship/ms-nair-feedback.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ms nair's feedback&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feedback is spot-on (I predicted as much back in May) and is absolutely
something that I need to work on. Ms Nair was also kind enough to lend me some
books that will hopefully teach me not to behave like one’s on the spectrum,
including “The 5 Languages of Appreciation in the Workplace”, “Emotional
Intelligence 2.0”, “The Rules of Management” and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was interviewed by the directors who asked me (among other things) whether I
would be OK with taking PPE. The CEO also asked me, although childhood
programming education is so important, students nowadays have so many
activities vying for their time. How can we then fit programming in? I answered
that it’s exactly the wrong approach to think of programming as a separate
subject. Instead it should be worked into maths, physics, chemistry, even
literature lessons—learning Cartesian coordinates through programming a game,
or learning about circuits through wiring up a Makey-Makey, or building a
chatbot that replies only in quotes from Shakespeare’s plays. I thought the
interview went well, and I can only suppose that it did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s curious that IMDA’s entire interview process did not include an aptitude
test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a rather semantic distinction, but I am the first IMDA scholar to be
attached to IMDA. There have been many local scholars (Marvin, Wei Heng, Gui
An) and many overseas IDA/MDA scholars but due to the fact that IDA and MDA
only just merged to form IMDA, I am the first one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will work hard these three years and fight for my First in Oxford. I will
live frugally off the allowance IMDA gives me and I aim to save 300 pounds
every month to start building my nest egg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;built-my-first-piece-of-native-production-software-using-electron&quot;&gt;Built my first piece of native production software using Electron&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From July 1 to ~August 15, I built &lt;a href=&quot;www.github.com/lieuzhenghong/inspectors-gadget&quot;&gt;Inspector’s
Gadget&lt;/a&gt;, a desktop app that
streamlines the process of generating building inspection reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was at my dad’s behest, who kept on complaining about how tedious it was
to do these reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, many firsts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time using Webpack&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time using Electron&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time using Vue&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time writing a program that stored persistent data (I used localForage,
a library over indexedDB)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time writing a “native” GUI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time using GitHub’s releases feature&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First time using Travis to do continuous integration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still want to learn:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to use tests and do test-driven development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A better way to package, deploy and release binaries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lieuzhenghong/inspectors-gadget/blob/master/what-i-learned.md&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
for a more comprehensive list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-plans&quot;&gt;Future plans&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have made my decision to go to Oxford and study PPE, and will not look back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goals set in May were to get a Class 3 driving license and to do at least
one machine learning project: I have not done a machine learning project by
August 2, 2017, nor will I be able to get a Class 3 driving license by 31
September 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter. I now have a new and very ambitious goal: to be accepted into Georgia Tech’s
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.omscs.gatech.edu/&quot;&gt;Online Master of Science Computer Science (OMSCS)&lt;/a&gt;
in three years’ time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote an email to the OMSCS admissions office asking “How can I make a
competitive application to OMSCS in three years’ time?” and was very pleased to
get a response back. I have only reproduced a small part of this (very
comprehensive) response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Applicants who do not meet the preferred qualifications for admission to the
OMS CS program – i.e. do not have an undergraduate degree in computer
science or related field (typically mathematics, computer engineering or
electrical engineering) AND/OR have a cumulative GPA of less than 3.0 – will
be evaluated on a case-by-case basis which includes your transcripts,
recommendation results, academic history, essays, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Having said that, in general, applicants are expected to be comfortable
programming (C or C++ are generally expected at a minimum) and to have had at
least several more advanced topics, such as Advanced OS, Networking, Theory,
and/or Algorithms. &lt;strong&gt;Usually, if the applicant does not have a CS degree, we
are looking for background that shows evidence that they have equivalent
skills (and remember an IT degree does not bring the same mix of skills as a
CS degree).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The main concern of the OMS CS Graduate Admissions Committee is
that prospective students have a competent computer science foundation. If a
prospective student feels they have sufficient work experience and/or
programming knowledge to provide this foundation (based on the OMS CS course
prerequisites), it is best to provide some sort of documentation
(recommendation letter, transcript, grade etc.) to verify their programming
skills. We also highly recommend that applicants include information
regarding relevant programming skills in their resume as well as their
application essays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We highly recommend prospective students review the prerequisites for courses
relevant to their OMS CS specialization interests and/or career interests to
determine if they have the foundation necessary to succeed in the OMS CS
program. &lt;strong&gt;If a prospective student is lacking in a certain area, we recommend
they determine which prerequisites are most critical for them to take and
then research whether or not they are available through their institution, an
accredited institution near them, or online through an accredited program
and/or MOOC from an accredited institution.&lt;/strong&gt; One useful resource may be
certified/graded MOOC’s offered through Class Central at the following
website http://www.class-central.com.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If a prospective student does pursue some prerequisite courses, we would
expect to see some sort of grade as part of the evaluation from the course
(some courses show a grade or percentile, others do not do any evaluation and
will not show their CS knowledge-base). &lt;strong&gt;Please note, completing coursework at
an accredited institution is recommended. Additionally, if you do take
prerequisite courses, it will likely strengthen your application more to have
prerequisite courses completed when you apply as grades verify you have
obtained the necessary skills to succeed in a graduate level CS program.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I have decided to dedicate the next three years to study the
equivalent of an undergraduate CS syllabus on my own, while studying
PPE at Oxford. I hear from my friends and OUMSSA “parents” that the workload
even for PPE is not too bad, but we’ll soon see. Securing a First of course
comes &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; but I believe that by paring the inefficiencies out of my life I
will be able to accomplish these two goals with aplomb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being an IMDA scholar could help me achieve these goals more easily. I won’t
have to waste my time looking for a job or an internship; I will (hopefully) be
given $3,000 to help finance the cost of attaining these certificates under
NIS’s Talent Development Programme; they will give me a 1 year—1.5 year
deferment before I start serving my bond at IMDA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tentatively, I will be following the syllabus outlined in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/open-source-society/computer-science&quot;&gt;Open Source
Society University’s CS
curriculum&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a
long road and I will need to start formally planning out my study roadmap very
soon, perhaps by the end of this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grind never ends—not after my As, not during army, not even after I have
gotten my scholarship. But I am beginning to realise that I may like and even
need this grind in my life more than I think I do.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="progress report" /><summary type="html">Since my last post I have done the following:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building a Raspberry Pi console</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/30/building-a-raspberry-pi-console.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building a Raspberry Pi console" /><published>2017-05-30T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-05-30T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/05/30/building-a-raspberry-pi-console</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/30/building-a-raspberry-pi-console.html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, Bailin and I finished the build of the Raspberry Pi console.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Raspberry Pi console project is the culmination of more than half a year of
effort. For the last eight months, I have been teaching the kids at Ulu Pandan
Stars Python (specifically Python Turtle). After much hand-holding and patient
instruction the kids were able to write the code for a Pong clone (mostly) all
by themselves. (We wrote the code that read from the GPIO pins).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kids don’t understand all the concepts, however, which makes me think that
the project is a little too ambitious. For example, they have no idea what the
ADC does, how the wiring in the Raspberry Pi works and/or how the Raspi reads
the hardware inputs. I don’t see this as &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; big a deal, though, because even
if they don’t understand it, at least they know about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, the kids definitely &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; understand a lot of things: basic
programming concepts (functions, loops, conditionals), Cartesian coordinates,
event-based programming, and so on. We have also been training them to talk
about what they have done (the girls lack the confidence to speak in a formal
setting) but there’s still a lot of work that still needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;parts-used&quot;&gt;Parts used&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7-inch touchscreen LCD: 118 SGD&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Raspberry Pi 3: ~65 SGD&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rheostats, 2: ~2 SGD each&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;60mm buttons, 2: 4.50 SGD each&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;45mm buttons, 2: 3.50 SGD each&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ADC, 3 (but we used only 1): ~7 SGD each&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Box file from Popular: ~5 SGD&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;X-acto knife: 13 SGD&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solder iron: given to me by Snoopy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total cost: ~250 SGD&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-draft&quot;&gt;First draft&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project started as a ‘shoebox console’ but we found that a shoebox was way
too flimsy. Here’s what that looked like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/old_console_closeup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/old_console_closeup2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/old_console_students.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image-title-here&quot; /&gt;
Zhengyang with the students&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;video width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/old_console_video&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video of me pressing the buttons&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used an X-acto knife to cut the holes in the box and had to solder wires
onto the rheostats and the push buttons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;improved-version&quot;&gt;Improved version&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bailin was able to buy a box file from Popular for $5 so we used that instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_wip_soldering.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Soldering the buttons&quot; /&gt;
Bailin soldering the buttons. His hands were shaky so I took over for the more
delicate parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_wip.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Work-in-progress console&quot; /&gt;
The box before we put all the stuff inside it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_wip_closeup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Closeup of the work-in-progress console&quot; /&gt;
Closeup of the WIP console; power bank not pictured&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_video&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video tour of the console&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_side.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Console from the side&quot; /&gt;
Side view&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_closeup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Closeup of the console&quot; /&gt;
Closeup of the console&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_gaming_video&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mom and my cousin playing with it: the game is buggy and I will get
Audrey and Gillian to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finishing-up&quot;&gt;Finishing up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I called for an extra lesson where I got the kids to mount the final two
buttons so they couldclaim to have done at least some of it themselves (instead
of having the tutors do all the work). Here’s what the final version looks like
now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_v2_front.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Console from the front&quot; /&gt;
Front view&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_v2_34.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Console from the side&quot; /&gt;
3/4-view. I think it &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareidolia&quot;&gt;kind of looks like a
face!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/raspi-console/console_v2_closeup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Closeup of the console&quot; /&gt;
Closeup of the console&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually I still don’t know how the thing is wired because Zheng Yang did the
lion’s share of the work in wiring. I’ll have to learn from Bailin how
everything is wired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my first time working with a Raspberry Pi as well as hardware
components like rheostats and buttons: my previous projects were all
software-only. I’m very grateful to Zheng Yang and Bailin for helping so much
(it literally could not have been done without Zheng Yang).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kids will finish their DSA exercise in August. Whether or not they get into
DSA is out of my control but I hope that they will have the confidence and
motivation to pursue similar projects in the future. STEM is the future, after
all…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kids should patch their games and do some bug-fixing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to build a few ‘demonstration games’ on the console that make
good use of the two rheostats (an interesting input medium).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s my hope that this console can be used as a springboard for future
programming lessons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="programming" /><category term="build" /><category term="making" /><category term="programming-education" /><summary type="html">Yesterday, Bailin and I finished the build of the Raspberry Pi console.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">May 2017 report</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/29/monthly-report-may-2017.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="May 2017 report" /><published>2017-05-29T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-05-29T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/05/29/monthly-report-may-2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/29/monthly-report-may-2017.html">&lt;p&gt;Since my 
&lt;a href=&quot;/2017/03/31/quarterly-report-2017.html&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; I have done the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finished my internship at iGlobe (ended May 12, 2017)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Been rejected by MAS and GIC in the penultimate round&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Went to Japan for the first time in my life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finished building the Raspberry Pi console&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finished my first substantial MOOC, Andrew Ng’s Machine Learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Built my first executable file (.exe rather than .py) and wrote &lt;em&gt;software&lt;/em&gt; rather than a &lt;em&gt;program&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these deserve a separate post so I’ll dedicate the whole of today to writing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finished-my-internship-at-iglobe&quot;&gt;Finished my internship at iGlobe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started interning at iGlobe on 23rd January 2017 and ended 12th May 2017. My
main responsibility was to help the investment team (Jeff) in his sourcing for
new deals. That means that I accompanied him to meetings with promising
startups and wrote minutes for the meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a later stage, this evolved into due diligence whereby I had to research on
the company to see if i) they could deliver on their promised claim; ii) they
did not misrepresent the uniqueness or impact of their technology; iii) there
were any other competitors in this market and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the final stage, I was tasked to help write &lt;strong&gt;investment papers&lt;/strong&gt; for the
company. Investment papers are papers written by the investment team for the
Board. They introduce the company and explain why the company is worth
investing in. I helped Jeff do in-depth research in the technology of the
company and wrote those sections of the investment paper. Over the course of my
internship I helped write investment papers for V-key, an online crpyto company
and SourceSage, an app for oleochemical traders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also tasked to do market research on industries iGlobe was interested in
(e.g. insurtech, fintech, blockchain). I produced three research reports on
insurtech, medtech and payment data monetisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the investor side, I helped the investor team conduct research on the
possibility of getting family offices to invest in iGlobe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also learned miscellaneous administrative stuff like how to use a courier
service, how to post a letter and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;programming-at-iglobe&quot;&gt;Programming at iGlobe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote two programs during my stint at iGlobe,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lieuzhenghong/form-letterer&quot;&gt;form-letterer&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lieuzhenghong/form-emailer&quot;&gt;form-emailer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These programs make it easy to send multiple similar emails (form emails) to
different recipients. As an intern, I was given drudgery like this to do and I
didn’t like it (I am a very lazy person). Therefore, I wrote these programs to
help me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Form Letterer takes in a specially-formatted Word document and a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.csv&lt;/code&gt; data
file, and returns multiple personalised Word documents. This is useful if you
want to be printing contracts for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Form Emailer automatically sends personalised emails to receipients, and
supports attachments as well. It can be used in conjuction with Form Letterer
to send each recipient a different Word document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These programs are actually quite trivial (form-letterer was actually harder
because of how difficult it is to manipulate Word documents programmatically!).
It was yet another example of, as Mark puts it, “library whacking”. However, I
still learned a lot from these projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I learned how to write code that is meant for the end-user. This
means catching exceptiosn and throwing ‘friendly’ error messages; being
permissive and clever when handling imperfect user input; building an
executable instead of leaving it as a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;program.py&lt;/code&gt; file (may write a separate
post on this); writing comprehensive and easy-to-read documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second of all, I learned how to use Python’s &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;argparse&lt;/code&gt; to write a command-line
program! I’ve never done this before and I’m very happy with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also happy with the fact that my code is clean and follows PEP-8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m slightly regretful that I didn’t manage to write a nice TUI/GUI. Instead I
used Python’s &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;input&lt;/code&gt; to prompt users to fill in their details instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the real test of any piece of software is: is it being used? And I
am happy to report that it is (for now…). I met Kim and her nephew at a calligraphy
competition yesterday and she told me that they successfully used it to send
their quarterly report without any help on my part!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I am very pleased to have written a piece of software that is
successfully being used by end-users. I’m also happy that I was able to
contribute to iGlobe above and beyond the help normally expected from an
intern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rejected-from-scholarships&quot;&gt;Rejected from scholarships&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was rejected from both GIC and MAS in the penultimate round, the ‘group
discussion’ round… perhaps my personality was too abrasive. Unfortunately the
scholarship agencies don’t give feedback on unsuccessful applications.
Nevertheless, it was a good learning experience; I don’t regret the application
process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last scholarship I am waiting for is IMDA. As of this moment, IMDA is
trying to schedule an interview slot with the directors. I told them that I
would be willing to cancel my trip to Yunnan if need be; nothing to do now but
wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-plans&quot;&gt;Future plans&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The path ahead of me is bifurcated. All depends on my decision to go to Ox or
NTU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are things that I will be doing no matter my eventual choice, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-very-clear-goals&quot;&gt;Some very clear goals:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get a Class 3 driving license by September 31 2017&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do at least one machine learning project by August 2 2017&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-more-nebulous-ones&quot;&gt;Some more nebulous ones:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think about a new niche for the Codellective: see &lt;a href=&quot;http://saturdaykids.com/creative-coder/pykids-level-1/&quot;&gt;this Saturday kids
class&lt;/a&gt; also doing
Python Turtle idea but they have a lot of traction and are charging 700-900
per workshop?? I think the real question is : what is Codellective, what are
we doing different from the rest, what kind of volunteers do we want?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pipe-dreams&quot;&gt;Pipe dreams:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pretty sure that these won’t happen&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn to play one of Faye Wong’s songs on the piano by 2nd Aug 2017—no point
asking Prof Chiu for the scores if I never use them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of a way to earn some money during university&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="progress report" /><summary type="html">Since my last post I have done the following:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2017 Quarterly Report I</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/03/31/quarterly-report-2017.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2017 Quarterly Report I" /><published>2017-03-31T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-03-31T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/03/31/quarterly-report-2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/03/31/quarterly-report-2017.html">&lt;p&gt;Wah. Really in a blink of an eye 3 months can pass just like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what have I been doing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In January I went on a trip to Cebu with my JC class. For only 1018 dollars I managed to get a diving license (although the license has yet to arrive after two months). It was a very good 9-day (or was it 8 days?) trip where I had nice food and got to try foods like Balut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diving was a really good experience and I want to go again, I will probably want to invest in a mask with prescription though because I couldn’t see shit until the sardine run dive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realised that traveling with a big group is not easy because different people have different wants. Nonetheless, the trip went relatively smoothly and I felt that I got closer with a few people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On January 23 I started the internship at iGlobe.
I think there is room for me to do more work.
This week will be the 2-month mark at iGlobe. I have been fortunate enough to be able to sit in for many meetings with investees and am learning a lot about different startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently working on a form letterer for iGlobe. Unfortunately, I predict that the uptake will be quite minimal. 
I’m not sure. Have to make it as easy to use as possible because the biggest obstacle to adoption is simply user laziness.
&lt;strong&gt;Update 31st March&lt;/strong&gt; Finished building the app and I may write a post about it. We’ll see. I’m the only one using it now&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February, I started on Andrew Ng’s Machine Learning MOOC. Have finished about 3/4th of it right now, and aim to revisit it soon…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;March was scholarship season and I have put the MOOCs on hold. I plan to resume in April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;scholarship-overview&quot;&gt;Scholarship overview&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;current-progress&quot;&gt;Current progress:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JTC: Rejected&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MAS: 2/4&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GIC: 2/4&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CAAS: 0/4 (went for first round, now waiting for result)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IMDA, PSC, EDB: Pending (not heard from them)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IE: forgot about it tbh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mas-scholarship&quot;&gt;MAS Scholarship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went for the first round of the MAS scholarship where we were tasked to write an essay about the two things I would change about Singapore and why. Then I had to take a psychometric test which was easy-peasy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have just came back from the second round of interview from MAS. I’m not sure if I will hear back from them. (Update 30 Mar: I did, third round is on Monday, 3 Apr)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the interview, I got to talk with a HR rep, Henry. Henry said that there were about 600+ applicants this year. They chose 150 for the first round. Out of those 100, 30-40 are in this secondround. When the fourth round begins, there are about eight candidatesand they will finally award the scholarship to 4-6 candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He confirmed that some years MAS does award 0 or 1 scholarships and in the distant past, more than 10 years ago, they awarded 10+ scholarships. The range nowadays is 4-6 though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is evidently a very selective process. Even now, I have only a 10%of getting the scholarship if we look at the numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the interviewers asked if I had any questions for them I asked for their feedback on my preformance and what I could do to improve. They were quite taken aback by this question and one person commented that I was the first to ask them that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interviewer said that she liked my candour because when they first asked me why MAS I just said that if I don’t get a scholarship I can’t go to Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two interviewers commented that in the future I should come prepared with an example of an MAS policy and be ready to defend it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HR person said that my mind spin too fast and my mouth cannot catch up. Sometimes I will leave the thread of one argument hanging and jump to the next one. And spoke too fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were the suggestions they had for improvement. I will definitely prepare more for future interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of them did say it’s obvious that I have a bright future and to keep in touch even if I don’t get the scholarship. (He quickly clarified that this does not impute anything about whether I had gotten the scholarship). But I’m pretty sure that this is something they say to every single candidate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I think I made a pretty unique impression (whether it was a &lt;strong&gt;good&lt;/strong&gt; impression is something else entirely). It could have gone better. It was a long interview though, one hour long, and my legs were shaking at the end of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;jtc-scholarship-short-and-perfunctory&quot;&gt;JTC scholarship: short and perfunctory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JTC scholarship interview was a group interview with 3 members of HR. They asked us rather silly questions like “what do you think of cyberbullying” and I was like diao… come and ask this kind of question…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it was quite funny when they asked us what scholarship we are applying for/ what scholarships we want to apply for and all of us basically just listed out macam shopping list like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They rejected me very swiftly—the evening of the interview, in fact—and at the risk of sounding sour grapes, I don’t think JTC would have been right for me, either. So no great loss there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It didn’t take much courage but I was able to get numbers of my fellow scholarship applicants, Jerry, Engracia and Jazreel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to talk about this right now but I think there is a fine line between pushing and jioing. It’s important to walk this line right and sometimes it may be easy to overstep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;caas-scholarship&quot;&gt;CAAS scholarship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met Bryce at the CAAS scholarship. CAAS scholarship was pretty fun, I liked it a lot. We weretasked to roleplay as civil servants of CAAS and there were two parts. First part was a debate on proposed legislature regulating drones and the other part was&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gic&quot;&gt;GIC&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 28th of March I went for the GIC interview. It was great that Mrs Hauw introduced me to Phionna who was able to allay somewhat my anxiety regarding the interview. I was interviewed by two people who were Yen Chen and… someone else I unfortunately forgot the name of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They asked me why I chose PPE given my interest in tech, about my work in iGlobe and similar questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also asked me three rather pointed questions. First, they asked to tell them about the greatest risk I have ever taken, to which I answered my choice to take ELL instead of Econs inJ1. Then they asked me about a time where I failed and I told them about my NS experience. Lastly, they asked what my greatest weakness was (I joked with them that my greatest weakness is that I’m too long winded, interviewers always tell me to hurry up) and I answered that I can be too blunt and I can be too honest. I volunteered my Malay Special Program experience&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The common comment was that they really appreciated my candiness/candour but they were still uncertain whether i was 100% into the job itself. At MAS they were worried about whether I would be able to do the drudgery and at GIC they said that the work at iGlobe doesn’t necessarily reflect the work I will be doing at GIC, which will be more spreadsheets and stuff and less startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;other-stuff&quot;&gt;Other stuff&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marc has really changed a lot after going for his internship. Among other things he has taught me about the importance of being assertive and charismatic. We made a promise to each other to seize oppportunities for daygame, really talk to other people, I have been trying to do so but not entirely successfully. I did miss out yesterday at the gym, there was a pretty girl and I didn’t get to talk to her although I wanted to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been making some gains in the gym but it’s predominately bench gains because God knows it’s the only lift I program properly… it’s harder to progress with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m glad that plans for going on a trip with the 6 offenders are finally in the works. We have bought the tickets and Nauxiy and I have planned a more-or-less fixed itinerary.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="progress report" /><summary type="html">Wah. Really in a blink of an eye 3 months can pass just like that.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2016</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/27/2016-in-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2016" /><published>2016-12-27T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-12-27T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2016/12/27/2016-in-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/27/2016-in-review.html">&lt;p&gt;2016 has been a long year and it’s hard to keep track of all the things I’ve
done. I started this blog (I think it’s more of a diary really) for the express
purpose of keeping track of what I have been doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;calendar-of-events-2016&quot;&gt;Calendar of events 2016&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This diary/blog has been a great help in remembering the things that I’ve done
this past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Month&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;What I did&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Jan&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;Nothing of note&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Feb&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;Nothing of note&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Mar&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;&lt;del&gt;Nothing of note&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Apr&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Started this blog, approached IDA&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;May&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Started teaching at Ulu Pandan Stars&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Jun&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Ran a pilot course of Python Titans at IDA.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Jul&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Started work on the WITS project (Automated transaction tracker)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Aug&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Continued working on WITS project, started Co{de}llective&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Sep&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Finished WITS project, Built Charge Bot&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Oct&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Started on MOOCs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Nov&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Started building CodeGL (CPU visualisation)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Dec&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Holiday with family, built Co{de}llective website&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-i-have-succeeded-at&quot;&gt;Things I have succeeded at&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gaining-programming-skill&quot;&gt;Gaining programming skill&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I’ve focused on improving my technical skill. I feel that I have
learned a lot but there’s still a billion things to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My focus this year has been on the Web and I don’t think that’s a bad thing &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt;
because the Web is so ubiquitous after all. However,
after taking CS50 and doing some C, I realise that it can be a lot of fun. I
think I want to move away from building websites as it has become somewhat trivial
with the advent of excellent front-end frameworks like Bootstrap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still enjoy
game and app development and am likely to continue pursuing it in the future but 
after dipping my toes in CS50 I think I would like to explore the more technical/
computer science aspect of development. That means ML/NN/AI/compilers? instead
of web development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will run through this year’s projects each in chronological order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;this-blog&quot;&gt;This blog&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it is&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-explanatory&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Github Pages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jekyll,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buying a domain name&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Configuring DNS settings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first technical project of 2016. Building a website was not new to me but
using frameworks and build tools to build a website was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the longest time my approach to building a site was to whack &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt;
and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;style.css&lt;/code&gt; files (have been doing it since Sec One), and they’ve never been
hosted under a custom domain name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;automated-transaction-tracker&quot;&gt;Automated transaction tracker&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it is&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An app built during NS for WITS made to solve the problem of overdue
loans. It is basically a digital 12-11 record/digital loan book that
tracks who made what loans and sends SMS messages to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system supports user auth and multiple stores. Supervisors can
create stores and invite storemen users to contribute to that store.
Only invited users can see and modify transactions of a store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I built a front-end UI for users to access through their phones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately nobody wanted to use it as it was simply
extra work (but I still got Silver).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building a REST app&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;React&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ExpressJS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MongoDB and Mongoose&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deploying on DigitalOcean&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Twilio API and how to send SMSes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;User authentication (token-based)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JSON Web Tokens (JWT)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hashing and salting passwords&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;General back-end concepts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the largest project of 2016! It was an extremely ambitious and extremely
tiring project. I had a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of trouble with it although now, looking back, it
seems pretty trivial. (More on this phenomenon next time.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing all the Express routers/routes was hard, the MongoDB database queries
even harder, and the React UI hardest of all! It was this project that made me
realise that back-end is actually not hard and much more fun than the front-end.
This was a watershed moment as previously the back-end was something extremely
mysterious and inaccessible to me; I remember in 2015 I had no idea what Dae Koon
was doing when we were doing the Smart Gallery app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;charge-bot&quot;&gt;Charge Bot&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it is&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A telegram bot that allows two players to play the childhood game of
Charge. It is basically a while loop running on a Heroku instance
that long polls the Telegram server for updates. (it is not a server,
it is a client)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Telegram Bot API&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Long polling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More REST practice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deploying on Heroku&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I built this simple Telegram bot a couple months after the Bot API was released.
The moment the Bot API was announced CKY and I immediately discussed building a 
bot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An extremely simple Telegram bot that took a deceptively long time to do. 
I must admit that the concept
of long polling gave me a lot of grief: I had initially implemented my long polling
function recursively but that caused a stack overflow after some time. (Can you
figure out how to write a long polling function in a non-recursive manner?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;codegl-or-a-failed-shenzhen-io-knockoff&quot;&gt;CodeGL, or a failed Shenzhen I/O knockoff&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it is&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A “game” that allows you to input assembler commands into an extremely
rudimentary text box.
These commands are fed into a virtual machine (built by Mark) and
run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I built a display showing the values of the 16 32-bit registers
so you can draw very rudimentary images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently working on a display for RAM as well as extending the
parser/language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;C++&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SDL&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minimal knowledge of how a CPU works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this incomplete project has not been touched for more than a month, I 
learned a lot from it. It was my first time writing C++ code and my first time doing anything
graphics library related (I used SDL). I was quite happy to actually be writing a
graphical application because I always had this impression that writing graphics
stuff was incredibly difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, it would have been incredibly difficult had I not taken the CS50 course,
which introduced me to C. Otherwise I’m sorry to say that the unfamiliar syntax
would have scared me off (not to mention &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;make&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cmake&lt;/code&gt;!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-i-have-failed-at&quot;&gt;Things I have failed at&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;going-to-the-gym-consistently&quot;&gt;Going to the gym consistently&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have made gains, but I could have made more had I been more disciplined and
less lazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Am still looking into a routine for 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;acca&quot;&gt;ACCA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a 500 dollar course with Marc and realised that 
a) accountancy is not for
me and 
b) my interest and comparative advantage lies elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I have decided to abandon this track indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Marc (or rather Marc’s dad) told me that an ACCA qualification is useful
for going into finance into the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;swimming-15km&quot;&gt;Swimming 1.5km&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After getting a couple of bad sunburns and falling sick I stopped swimming with
Wei Liang. I can swim freestyle much more comfortably than I could before I started
swimming this year but my stroke is still poor and there’s a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not like swimming in public pools because they are crowded and gross.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I will pick this up in the future as a hobby and to get tan but I don’t
foresee swimming becoming a part of my life anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learning-to-drive&quot;&gt;Learning to drive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did not learn to drive. I had better things to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will definitely have to learn sooner or
later… am thinking of learning it in May after my internship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-that-are-neither-here-nor-there&quot;&gt;Things that are neither here nor there&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reading-50-books-in-a-year&quot;&gt;Reading 50 books in a year&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have actually succeeded in this endeavour (47 books–close enough) but I am 
parking this here as I do not feel
that this was a good use of my time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong – I love books – but I didn’t feel like I really got anything
from them. Because&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For skills like programming, reading books is not as useful
as doing and reading articles/code examples online. There are of course excellent
books like the Gang of Four’s 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Design_Patterns&quot;&gt;Design Patterns&lt;/a&gt; or JS: The Good Parts
but 
these books are meant more as
reference guides, so in what sense can you say to have “finished” them?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Low retention. Looking at the book list I kept for this entire year,
I realise that I have forgotten most of the content of the books. I did not use 
to have this problem because I would reread books again and again until I had 
internalised completely the concepts of the books. But this year, in an effort to
hit the completely arbitrary number 50 (and also because I like buying new books),
I did not do this.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Is there anything that can be done to remedy this? I read that you are not 
 supposed to read non-fiction books the same way you read fiction books – that
 is, from cover to cover, page 1 to end. Instead you should selectively skim
 the book for information and actively summarise/take notes while reading. I
 did not do this and do not like doing this largely because it feels too much
 like &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt; but I may have to give this method a try in the future. I did
 make some attempt at taking down notes but they were largely perfunctory and
 shit.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;teaching-at-ulu-pandan-stars&quot;&gt;Teaching at Ulu Pandan Stars&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truth be told, I did not very much enjoy the front part of teaching where I was
preparing them for the CodeXtreme hackathon. Many of the kids were simply not able
to learn any substantial programming concepts. I became much happier and far more
excited when I was able to pull out the four kids and try out my own curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that we have a clear goal for the kids – prepping them for DSA – is 
also extremely motivating. I am an extremely goal-oriented person and it helps me
greatly in my week-to-week planning if I have something in the future to look 
forward to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have filed this under “neither here nor there” because although the kids have 
already learned a lot, I have not delivered results yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;co-founding-codellective&quot;&gt;Co-founding Co{de}llective&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will reserve judgement/comment on this as it’s too early to say anything about
it right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;areas-for-improvement&quot;&gt;Areas for improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-management&quot;&gt;Time management&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that I did a lot of things this year but not very efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have improved greatly in that I do not slack off as much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is another subtle time-wasting bad habit I am guilty of and that is
my constant multitasking on the computer. It’s much more insidious because you 
think that you’re being productive and doing a lot of work but in reality you
haven’t established the Csikszentmihalyi-an “flow state” or “deep work” or
“intense focus” or whatever you want to call it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have had extremely occasional states whereby I was completely focused on the
task, be it reading a book or writing blog posts/code. 
Code is a little bit harder because it
necessitates a lot of SO and asking people for hep and that inherently breaks 
one’s rhythm. But there is no excuse for reading a book because I frequently got
distracted by small things like looking a word up on Pleco only to start replying
to Telegram messages, then going on Reddit… and even if the distraction lasts
only a few seconds, the flow state has been broken and productivity takes a 
nosedive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;completionist-streak&quot;&gt;Completionist streak&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to finish what you started and don’t be bantuerfei
but I have found that such one-dimensional thinking is not entirely
accurate either. Yes, I used to have (and still do have) the problem
of starting things or having goals and then not completing them. I 
identified this tendency early and made it my goal to drive this habit
out of my life by any means possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I realised after talking with Mark and reading some stuff online
like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pgbovine.net&quot;&gt;Prof Guo&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://freakonomics.com/podcast/new-freakonomics-radio-podcast-the-upside-of-quitting/&quot;&gt;this Freakonomics podcast&lt;/a&gt;
that a single-minded focus on trying to complete something that’s honestly
not worth your time is actually counterproductive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was doing the course CS50 I complained to Mark that although the front few
lessons were very educational, the later webdev lessons were not as they covered
ground that I already know. Mark told me that there’s no need to finish the course,
just like there’s no need to finish reading books or textbooks. The most important
thing is to get the information and learn as much as you can from the resource; 
it isn’t important at all if you “finish” it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I have had a change in thinking and am no longer adamant about finishing the
CS50 course. However, I will still do Problem Set 8 and the Final project because
I think those two problem sets are educational for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the challenge is in being able to identify which goals are not worth
pursuing or completing because I don’t learn from them, 
and which goals I don’t &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; like completing because they
are boring, difficult or hard to measure progress toward. It’s still 
very important to be able to “finish strong” (Prof Guo’s words,
not mine), of course, and this grit is a quality that I have to continue to cultivate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am happy with the way 2016 went. I have been productive and I have achieved the
goals I care most about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also just as important is the fact that I have tried new things and quit them 
when I realised that I did not care about them at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the risk of this blog post sounding like an Oscar acceptance speech:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am
extremely grateful to Mark, without whom all the aforementioned technical projects 
would be impossible to complete. He has gotten me unstuck more times than I can count
and possesses an incredible patience for putting up with my incessant questions.
Also, for hosting me at his house many times.
(The same goes for Wei Heng, minus the hosting me at his house part).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to CKY for being my best friend and being the only person I can 
bounce my silly game design/writing/business ideas off of. I also admire him greatly for
being extremely prolific and driven in his field of game design and development
and I hope that some of that productivity will rub off on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ariel has helped me a lot as an enthusiastic and responsive sounding-board for
my ideas. More than anyone else I have shared with her my ideas and concerns
about the Co{de}llective and Python Titans projects and she has always given me
good advice and honest feedback. She also spent two weekends of her time to 
help me run the nerve-wracking pilot program at IDA (on extremely short notice,
no less). I cannot thank her enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have Ming Shi to thank for introducing me to Ulu Pandan Stars and Mrs Hauw and
I owe him a meal. And speaking of Mrs Hauw, I must also be grateful to her for
giving me so much free rein with the C4C P5 class and for giving me the opportunity
to intern at her company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Sean, for helping me do my WITS poster despite his NS commitments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have thanked all these people for their contribution to my goals but I’d also
like to point out that I enjoy their company greatly and am grateful for that, too.
To that end, I’d like to thank all of my friends for being patient 
with my flaws, honest with their feedback, and liberal with their company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s to 2017!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="annual review" /><category term="progress report" /><summary type="html">2016 has been a long year and it’s hard to keep track of all the things I’ve done. I started this blog (I think it’s more of a diary really) for the express purpose of keeping track of what I have been doing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2015</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/26/2015-in-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2015" /><published>2016-12-26T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-12-26T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2016/12/26/2015-in-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/26/2015-in-review.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I wrote this last year in a Google Doc before this blog existed. I think before
I go about writing 2016’s Year in Review I should post this one, for completeness.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2015 has come to an end and I think it’s a good idea to write down the big things that have transpired this year and what I can look forward to in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year was the transition from student to NSF and the transition has not been entirely pleasant. Although I’m quite pleased with my current vocation and job scope I have a slipped disc and a fucked-up wrist to show for my troubles. I did not have a good time in BMT but I have met some new acquaintances and we meet up occasionally. I’m on OK terms with my colleagues at work as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other large event was of course  my trip to Oxford and I think this was the highlight of the year in terms of personal growth. I think it gave me a real new perspective with regard to interpersonal relationships and it got me out of my rut as well. It wasn’t the trip per se that was really helpful as much as it was the months of reading books and writing notes. It made the wait in army more bearable, I learned a lot, and i think that I should continue with this attitude of learning in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the things I think I did quite well in 2015 were the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did well in creating a budget and meticulously documenting my spending, and am accurate to the dollar. I will be improving the spreadsheet in 2016 by tracking my spending by category (the abortive attempt to create the Pennywise budgeting app has been shelved indefinitely) and using some graphs as well which will be quite cool hehe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did well in reading a lot of books in preparation for Oxford and although I don’t have anything to prepare for anymore I have set a goal of reading 48 books this year - that’s four books a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t do so well in the realm of interpersonal relationships. I guess part of this is inevitable because all my close friends are splitting up and going for NS and of course the girls are going to uni and all that. I don’t feel like I’m that close with my colleagues in the workplace either. And of course I’m still single but I’m honestly not that bothered despite all the noise I make about it because (i) my previous experience has made me realise that it’s hard to find a partner who shares a lot of my values and (ii) I should concentrate on self-improvement rather than chasing tail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of which, 20 is a significant milestone. It should be a portent of greater maturity now that I’ve crossed over into adulthood. Every year I tell myself that I should play less computer games and it never happens… because my friends are very bad influences…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>lieuzhenghong</name></author><category term="annual review" /><category term="progress report" /><category term="goal setting" /><summary type="html">I wrote this last year in a Google Doc before this blog existed. I think before I go about writing 2016’s Year in Review I should post this one, for completeness.</summary></entry></feed>